[Music]
[Musique]
Why can't we demand the
pourquoi on n pas capable d'exiger le
same level of financial security as we
même degré de sécurité financière qu'on
demand nuclear security, even though the
exige de sécurité nucléire alors que les
risks are still
risques sont quand même même de
[Music]
[Musique]
significant? Good morning, gentlemen. We have
grandeur bonjour messieurs nous avons
decided
décid
to hold this meeting to discuss the
à cette réunion pour parler des
United States, and more specifically,
États-Unis et plus particulièrement de
the
l'économie
American economy. We have
américaine nous avons un notre table
Hervé de Carnois at our table, who will now
Hervé de Carnois qui va prendre la
speak. Hervé, what can you
parole Hervé qu'est-ce que vous pouvez
tell us about the main
nous dire sur les principaux indicateurs
American economic indicators? Their accuracy,
économiques américains leur véracité
their reliability? Do they
leur leur ténacité est-ce qu'ils font
actually convey
réellement passer une information
correct or incorrect information? What do you
correcte pas correcte qu'est-ce que vous
think? The American economy is experiencing
pensez l'économie américaine est en
slight growth,
croissance légère à des
partly renewing its
renouvelle en
internal power
son sa puissance intérieure à
through a very
travers un niveau
[Music]
[Musique]
significant level of inventiveness. And it's a market of 310
important et c'est un marché de 310
million people with three pillars
millions de personnes avec trois pôles
of power. The first pillar is
de puissance hein premier pôle de
the military, the second is
puissance c'est l'armée le deuxème pôle
finance, and the third is
de puissance c'est la finance le trè p
technology. They
de puissance et la technologie et ils
are closely linked. So, will
sont intimement liés
the American economy
donc est-ce que l'économie américaine va
continue with weak growth?  I
continuer à une faible croissance je
would say it's likely, and their
dirais que c'est probable et que leur
main handicap is finance.
principal handicap est la finance
Phipéch, what can you
phipéch qu'est-ce que vous pouvez nous
tell us about this American growth,
dire sur cette croissance américaine
Estelle Scine? On what basis has
Estelle Scine sur qu sur quelle base
this growth been
cette croissance se
founded since 2009? It's clear that the
fonde depuis 2009 il est clair que les
massive and successive injections from the
injections massives et successives de la
Fed have certainly contributed to a
Fed ont certainement contribué à une
form of stimulus, but a somewhat
forme de relance mais un petit peu
indirect one, since it's actually through government
indirect puisque c'est au travers en
spending made
fait des dépenses de l'État que
possible by printing money.
l'impression monétaire a rendu possible
So, we'll say it's not
donc on va dire que c'est pas une
autonomous growth. Since 2010, there's been a very
autonome depuis 2010 il y a une très
clear increase in the
nette montée en puissance euh de la
production
production
of unconventional energy, what we
d'énergie non conventionnelle ce qu'on
call the famous
appelle les fameux gaz de
shale gas, which ensures relative
schiste qui assure une relative
independence, or at least allows
indépendance ou en tout cas permettre
the United States to make
aux États-Unis de faire quand même de
significant
grosses
savings in terms of
économies en terme de d'échange
foreign trade, so no waste of
extérieur donc pas de gaspillage de
resources. So, we'll say that this is
ressources donc on dire que là c'est de
growth through
la croissance par économie
induced economies. As for the rest, well, indeed,
induite pour le reste et bien
between finance, the
entre finance
arms lobby, and I would add
lobby de l'armement puis j'ajouterai
the powerful
quand même la puissante machine
Hollywood machine, since
hollywoodienne puisque les
audio rights represent
droits audio ça représente quand même
something quite significant in the
quelque chose de non négligeable aux
United States.  We
États-Unis donc on a
effectively have, let's say,
effectivement on va dire
three and a half pillars to support
trois piliers et demi pour soutenir une
growth—and I want to emphasize this, I think
croissance je veux le préciser je pense
Olivier will certainly say something about it—
qu'Olivier en dira certainement un mot
growth that isn't
une croissance qui n'est pas du tout
creating jobs at all. Olivier de la Marche,
créatrice d'emploi Olivier de la marche
today we're in a
aujourd'hui on est euh on est dans un
system where, roughly, you need about six
système où euh il faut à peu près euh 6
dollars of debt to generate one dollar of
dollars de dett pour faire un dollar de
GDP. So, I don't get
PIB en gros donc euh j'ai pas
the impression that this is a
l'impression que ce soit un système qui
sustainable system in the medium and long
soit soutenable à moyen terme et à long
term.
terme
You're dealing with something that is,
euh vous êtes sur quelque chose qui est
I would say, solely
euh qui est uniquement euh je dirais
state-run. Between
étatique c'est-à-dire que on a eu entre
1998 and 2008, American households were accumulating
98 et 2008 on a eu les ménages
$1 trillion in debt per year. Well, in 2008, that was the end
milliards de dollars par an bon 2008 fin
of it. They stopped because they were
du jeu ils arrêtent parce qu'ils sont
over-indebted and they started
surendettés et qu'on commence à les
evicting them from their homes, their cars, and so
virer de leur maison de leur voitures et
on. So, that was the
compagnie donc
end of it. What happened?
euh fin du jeu qu'est-ce qui s'est passé
Well, the state took over.
bah vous avez l'État qui a pris le
of that, and which has become heavily
relais de ça et qui s'est copieusement
indebted in the space of 4 or 5 years, so, uh, at a
endetté en l'espace de 4 ans 5 ans donc
rate of approximately 1
euh à raison à peu près d'ailleurs de de
trillion dollars per year,
de 1000 milliards dollars par par an
so you're talking about something where
donc vous êtes sur quelque chose qui
every single dollar of GDP is made up of
chaque chaque dollar de PIB et est fait
government debt, so I think
par de la dette d'État donc je pense que
it won't go very far like this.
ça n'ira pas très très loin comme ça
Olivier Beruer, I'd like your
Olivier beruer je voudrais votre
position on
position sur la nouvelle position de
Jeanette Kellen's new stance on Quantitative
Jeanette Kellen sur le Quantitative
Easing. What can you
Easing qu'est-ce que vous pouvez nous
tell us about it? Well, we understand that
dire dessus euh bon on a bien compris
quantitative easing will obviously
qu'évidemment le quantitétive easing va
continue. The United States is, in any case,
se poursuivre les États-Unis sont de
through the FEA (Federal Economic Federation), in a near
toute façon via la fê dans quasi
impossibility of stopping
impossibilité d'arrêter le
quantitative easing. We know that as soon as
quantittativeing on c'est bien dès
they pull the plug, you'll have enormous shocks
qu'ils vont débrancher vous allez avoir
on the stock market. There will be
des sousbressau énormes au niveau de la
major consequences for
Bourse c'est des conséquences majeures
financial companies. To get back to the
financières pour en revenir sur la
GDP part, well, as Olivier said, these
partie PIB bon comme l'a dit Olivier ces
last three years it's 500
trois dernières années c'est 500
billion in growth, it's 3 trillion in...
milliards de croissance c'est 3000
Debts, therefore a return that is
milliards de dettes donc un rendement
not very interesting at the very least.
pour le moins pas très intéressant
Second axis, this is perhaps highlighted from
deuxème axe ça c'est pe souligné issu
the work of Emmanuel 16 who looks quite
des travaux d'Emmanuel 16 qui regarde
closely at what is happening on
d'assz près ce qui se passe sur les sur
the inequalities in the United States. In the United States,
les inégalités aux ÉtatsUnis Unis qui
additional growth in
dit croissance supplémentaire ces
recent years means in return an
dernières années dit en contrepartie
increase in purchasing power, an
augmentation du pouvoir d'achat
increase in wages, this is the
augmentation des salaires c'est c'est la
counterpart of this growth. He
contrepartie de C de cette croissance il
looked at what fraction of
a regardé quelle était la fraction de
the increase over the last 3 years, all of which was
l'augmentation depuis 3 ans tout ce a
newly created, was captured by
été créé de nouveau qui a été capté par
the richest 1% in the United States and
le 1 % le plus riche aux États-Unis et
he arrived at this rather amusing figure
il est arrivé à ce chiffre assez amusant
of 120%.  In other words, the richest 1%
de 120 %. autrement dit le 1 % le plus
has captured all the wealth that has been
riche a capté toute la richesse qui a
created and, on top of that, has continued to siphon off
été créée et en plus a continué à piquer
the wealth and
sur la richesse et les les revenus la
income of the poorest 99%.
part de revenu des 99 % les plus pauvres
This simply means that in the
ce qui veut simplement dire que les
United States, 99% of the population has been
États-Unis c'est 99 % de la population
in recession since
qui est toujours en récession depuis
2009, while the 1% is doing much better. Indeed,
2009 et 1 % où ça va beaucoup mieux
when you average
effectivement quand on fait la moyenne
all of this from a distance, you might say, "Well, yes, it's growing
de tout ça vu de loin on dire bah oui ça
a little," but it's as if,
croit un petit peu mais c'est comme si
in terms of imagery, you were saying there's
en terme d'image on disait qu'il y a une
fabulous growth in Washington while the
croissance fabuleuse à Washington et
rest of the country is in recession.
tout le reste du pays est en récession
And on average, yes, on average it's still
et en moyenne oui en moyenne c'est quand
positive because the weight captured
même positif parce que le poids capté
by the 1% is phenomenal in the
par le 1 % est est phénoménal aux
United States;
États-Unis
it's
c'est
undeniable. How can Americans
indiscutable comment les Américains ont
see wealth disparities
capacité de voir les écarts de fortune
multiplying
se multiplier par des multiples
considerably? They accept it, right? They
considérables euh il l'acceptte hein il
accept it. And what do these Americans do? Do they
l'acceptte et que font ces Américains
invest abroad?
est-ce qu'ils investissent à l'étranger
No, very little. Do they make...
non très peu
Many donations have multiplied sixfold in the last
beaucoup ils se sont multipliés par 6
ten years. Do they
depuis 10 10 an est-ce qu'ils
invest cautiously in their own country?
investissent dans leur propre pays avec
They make investments, but are they
précaution hein ils ils font des
concerned about job creation? Very
concernés par la création d'emploi très
little. Do they want to pursue
peu est-ce qu'ils veulent aller
new patents and
vers les brevets nouveaux et les
inventions? Generally speaking,
inventions nouvelles généralement donc
if you want to invest well, you
et enfin si vous voulez bien investir il
need an investor and you need a
faut un investisseur et il faut une
bank, you need something else, of course.
banque hein il faut autre chose bien sûr
But the banking system remains
or le système bancaire reste
fragile, not very
fragile peu
entrepreneurial,
entrepreneurial
and so the image that emerges from
et donc l'image qu'on qui ressort de
all this is a mixed one.
tout ça est une image mitigé
Hervé, I'd like to follow up again.
Hervé je rebondis encore est-ce que vous
Can you tell us about the
pouvez nous parler des chiffres du
American unemployment figures? How
chômage américain comment comment
are they calculated? What is the
sont-il calculés qu quel quelle est la
veracity of these figures? When we
véracité de ces chiffres quand on
look at the FBOR (Federal Bureau of Labor Statistics) and the
regarde le le le bureau fbor sur la
methodology used, we realize that
méthode faite on se rend compte qu'il y
almost 1 million unemployed people have been
a pratiquement 1 million de chôeurs qui
removed from the lists. This has an impact on
sont sortis des liste ça ninfluence sur
the last
le dernier trimestre sur le dernier
quarter. Thank you, Hervé. Hervé, what
trimestre merci Hervé Hervé qu'est-ce
can you tell us about this? That
que vous pouvez nous dire
the Americans, as
dessus que que les Américains euh comme
always, prioritize image over substance.
toujours gèent l'image avant le contenu
All sectors, you know, I mean
dans tous les domaines hein je veux dire
it's a trend of the last 50
c'est une tendance des 50 derniers
years. So, they present
dernires années bon donc il présente une
as positive an image as possible of
image aussi positive que possible de
their unemployment, which is around 7.6%, whereas
leur chômage qui est autour de 7,6 %
10 years ago it was around
hein qui était il y a 10 ans autour de 4
4.5 to 5%, so it has
et5i 5 % donc qui s'est
deteriorated. Americans are
détérioré les Américains se trouvent
facing a dilemma they can't seem to
devant un dilemme qu'il n'arrivent pas à
solve, and that dilemma is how do
résoudre et ce dilemme est comment
we increase the wealth being created
augmentons-nous la richesse qui se crée
and employment? But currently, in
et emploi or à l'heure actuelle dans
industry and services, the
l'industrie et dans les services de la
wealth being created isn't
richesse secrée elle n'est pas
generating
génératrice
jobs. Mr. de la Marche,
d'emploi monsieur de la marche est-ce
could you give us a little
que vous pouvez nous déléger un petit
more of the unemployment figures? And
peu plus les chiffres du chômage et
then, Mr. Béchad,
ensuite monsieur béchad est-ce que vous
could you talk to us about municipal bonds
pouvez nous parler des municipal bonds
and student debt? Olivier, I have
et de la dette étudiante Olivier j'ai
bad news for Mr.
une mauvaise nouvelle pour Monsieur
Bernard: buying back bonds doesn't
Bernand c'est pas en rachetant des
lower
obligation vous faites baisser le
unemployment. He believed it for a
chômage alors il l'a cru pendant un
while, or rather, he pretended to believe it,
moment ou il a fait semblant d'y croire
but apart from the trader you're going to...
mais à part le trader que vous allez
Hiring someone to press the button... I don't
engager pour appuyer sur le bouton je
see who else could be hired
vois pas qui peut être engagé de plus
to lower unemployment. We
pour faire baisser le chômage on est on
have American unemployment figures,
a des chiffres du chômage
we have all the statistics.
américain on a toutes les statistiques
That's the advantage of the United States; you don't
c'est l'avantage des États-Unis vous ne
have them in Europe, for example, where
les avez pas en Europe par exemple où on
you're also given a figure that's far
vous donne aussi un chiffre qui est loin
from reality, except you don't have
de la réalité sauf que vous n'avez pas
the means to verify it. In the United States,
les moyens de le vérifier aux États-Unis
you have the means to verify it, and
vous avez les moyens de le vérifier et
it's quite easy. The
c'est assez assez facile les
statistics are quite well done. So
statistiques sont assez bien faites donc
today, if we recalculate things
aujourd'hui si on recalcule les choses
with the average labor force
avec le taux moyen du taux de
participation rate in the
participation à la population active de
United States, you arrive at
de de aux États-Unis vous retomber sur
figures that are, broadly speaking,
des chiffres qui sont au sens large hein
the component that they call U6,
donc la la composante qu' appellent U6
broadly speaking, that is to say, people who have
au sens large c'est-à-dire les gens qui
completely left the workforce, people who
sont complètement sortis les gens qui
are receiving benefits, and so on. You're
sont indemnisés plus et cetera vous êtes
around 18 to 19% unemployment
autour de entre 18 et 19 % de chômage
in the United States. That's one in
aux États-Unis ça fait un Américain sur
five Americans. Obviously, you
5 alors évidemment ça d'ailleurs vous
can corroborate this figure by the number
pouvez corroborer chiffre par le nombre
of Americans who are on welfare.
d'Américains qui sont au foot stamp hein
You have roughly one...  A little
vous en avez à peu près un petit peu
less than 50 million, so that's a little
moins de 50 millions donc c'est-à-dire
less than
un petit peu moins de 15 % autour autour
15% of the population.
de 15 % de la population
So you're in a
euh donc vous êtes sur une sur un un un
country that, by definition, cannot
un pays qui par définition ne peut
create value, create
pas créer de la de la valeur créer du
GDP, except through debt, and
PIB autrement que par la dette et
except through government debt.
autrement que par la dette d'État
So I would say now there are
donc je dirais maintenant c'est c'est il
really no more questions to answer.
y a il y a vraiment plus de question à
You have companies that
seoser vous avez des entreprises qui
continue to lay off people; there are
continuent à virer du monde il y a des
announcements almost every day.
annonces à peu près tous les jours
Why? Well, because they're trying to
pourquoi bah parce que elles essaie de
maintain margins while their revenues are
conserver des marges alors qu'elles ont
falling. So it
des chiffres d'affaires qui baissent
will stop at some point, we know that,
donc ça s'arrêtera à un moment ça on le
because once you have the
sait hein puisque une fois que vous avez
president and the CEO left in the company, it's a bit short-lived. So it will stop at some point,
l'entreprise le président et l'Ô Tesse
but it
donc ça s'arrêtera à un moment mais ça
will stop with a high rate that won't
s'arrêtera avec avec un taux élevé et
decrease;
qui ne baissera pas qui ne baissera pas
in any case, we'll never see those
en tout cas on ne retrouvera jamais les
rates again.  Before, that is to say, the
taux d'avant c'est-à-dire le taux de
full employment rate which was around 4% in the
plein emploi qui était autour de 4 % aux
United States, you won't find that again,
États-Unis vous ne le retrouverez pas
Philippe. Municipal bonds,
Philippe les municipal bonds la dette
student debt... so I'll start, indeed, perhaps
étudiante alors je vais commencer
with
effectivement peut-être par la dette
student debt, which allows us to pick up on what
étudiante qui permet de rebondir sur ce
Queivier just said. So we have a
queivier vient de dire donc on a un
labor market that isn't becoming more fluid in the United
marché du travail qui ne se fluidie pas
States,
qui ne se fluidifie pas aux États-Unis
naturally, since companies
naturellement puisque les entreprises
are reluctant to
sont réticentes à
hire, knowing full
embaucher dans la mesure où elles savent
well that the
bien que les
natural market opportunities, at least for
débouchés naturel en tout cas le
consumers in the United States, are currently
consommateur aux États-Unis il est pour
almost
l'instant presque
locked down, sequestered,
presque verrouillé séquestré
sequestered. So a job market that isn't
séquestré donc un marché de l'emploi qui
opening up to
ne s'ouvre pas qui ne s'ouvre pas aux
young people, obviously, that makes things
jeunes évidemment ça rend les choses
complicated. What are young people doing
compliqué qu'est-ce que font les jeunes
today? They're extending the length of their
aujourd'hui ils allongent la durée des
studies. Now, let's say that the
études maintenant on va dire que la
norm has become a Master's degree, whereas
norme c'est devenu le master alors que
when you had a Bachelor's or
quand on était au niveau Licence ou
Master's degree, you could easily find a
maîtrise on trouvait facilement de
job. You could still go further,
l'emploi on pouvait encore approfondir
but you had to have the means. Does this
mais fallait avoir les moyens est-ce que
represent a risk for banks
ça représente un risque pour les banques
that this market of future students won't  They ca
que ce marché des futurs étudiants ne
n't find work and can't
trouvent pas de travail et ne puisse pas
repay, roughly what
rembourser ça représente à peu près quel
volume of debt does that represent? Student debt is
volume de dette la dette étudiante c'est
1.3 trillion to my knowledge, but
1300 milliards à ma connaissance mais
the banks risk
alors voilà les banques ne risquent là
absolutely nothing since the
strictement rien puisque la
special feature of pre-student loans is that they
particularité des présétudiants c'est
are actually guaranteed by the state.
qu'ils sont en fait garantis par l'État
But it's inevitable that sooner or
mais il a bien Fall qu'un jour ou
later someone will foot the bill.
l'autre quelqu'un paye l'ardoise or ce
Now, what we call the potential default rate on pre-student loans is
sur les prèétudiants aujourd'hui il est
officially 12.5%, but it's actually
officiellement de 12.5 il est en réalité
20%, or 20%, or 25%. So, 25%, 2.3
de 20 % ou 20 ou 25 donc 25 % 2300
trillion. Okay, let's calculate roughly that,
Milliards bon on va calculer grosso modo
it will be 250 billion, the
ça fera de 250 milliards la charge de
state's burden. We'll have to find this 250
l'État il faudra trouver ces 250
billion; it doesn't exist, so we'll have to find a way around it. As
milliardes il n'existe pas donc planche
for munibonds, we
concerne les munibonds alors là on a
recently witnessed, in
assisté tout récemment c'était
mid-November, one or two rather
mi-novembre à une ou deux journées un
unusual days while
petit peu particulières pendant que
Ms. Yelen was having her hearing before
madame Yelen passait son audition devant
the US Senate. And during this...  At
le Sénat américain et bien pendant ce
that time, the banks—I imagine the
temps-là les banques j'imagine les
major investors, the families—were
grands investisseurs les familles office
massively liquidating
liquidit massivement les obligations
municipal bonds, so massively that it was
municipales si massivement que c'était
almost historic. We hadn't seen
presque historique Onon avait pas vu de
such waves of liquidations since
Tell vagues de liquidation depuis
the fall of 2008. What this means is that
l'automne 2008 qu'est-ce que ça veut
after
dire c'est que après
Detroit, Cleveland, Acron, and so many
Detroit Cleveland acron et tant
other municipalities and counties in the
d'autres municipalités et cté du Nord
industrial Northeast of the United States, we
Est industriel des États-Unis on
realize that there are also many
s'aperçoit qu'il y a aussi plein de
bankrupt municipalities in
municipalités en faillite également en
California, as well as in
Californie qu' en a aussi en Caroline du
South Carolina, pretty much everywhere. And
Sud qui y en a à peu près partout et que
there too, we see that the situation is not
là aussi on voit que la situation ne
improving, for reasons we've
s'améliore pas et pour des raison qu'on
already mentioned. That is to say, since we
a déjà évoqué c'est-à-dire que comme on
have 18 to 19% of Americans unemployed, the
a 18 à 19 % d'Américains sans emploi les
municipalities are still doing their
municipalités font quand même leur
best, obviously, to provide some
possible évidemment pour apporter un
support, which costs money. And the second
soutien donc ça ça coûte et la deuxème
thing is that taxes aren't coming in
chose c'est que les taxes ne rentrent
because people who have been evicted
pas puisque des gens qui ont été virés
from their homes or their cars, as has
de leur maison ou de leur voiture comme
been said, these people are also not in a position
cela a été dit euh ces gens-là sont pas
to...  Paying neither
non plus en moyen de payer ni les taxes
local taxes nor local duties, uh,
locales ni les impôts locaux
the tax base, the base of
euh le la base taxable la base des gens
taxable people, is shrinking, those who remain
taxables se réduisant ceux qui restent
are squeezed much more,
sont pressurés de façon beaucoup plus
even unbearably, so
importante voire insupportable donc
they end up leaving the city and
ceuxa finissent par quitter la ville et
going elsewhere. So we have a kind
aller ailleurs donc on a là une espèce
of spiral here, and I really don't see how we
de spirale dont je ne vois vraiment pas
can get out of it. On the other hand,
comment comment on peut sortir en
if the municipalities go
revanche si les municipalités font
bankrupt, obviously the State will bail them out
faillite évidemment l'État renfloura
with what? With freshly
avec quoi avec de l'argent fraîchement
printed money. Olivier, uh, yeah, I'd like to
imprimé Olivier euh ouais moi j'aimerais
comment on the employment aspect. It's
réagir sur sur la partie emploi c'est
really interesting what's happening
vraiment intéressant ce qui se passe
there in the United States.
là-bas au aux États-Unis
Uh, when we look at it clearly,
euh quand on regarde de façon indbutable
the number of unemployed has decreased. There are
le nombre de chômeurs a baissé il y a
fewer unemployed in the United States. Now,
moins de chômeurs aux États-Unis après
what is an unemployed person? An unemployed person is
c'est quoi un chômeur un chômeur c'est
someone who obviously doesn't work
quelqu'un qui évidemment ne travaille
and declares they want to work, and that
pas et déclare vouloir travailler et ça
population has decreased. On the other hand, what
cette population là a baissé par contre
has exploded is the number of
ce qui a explosé c'est le nombre de
people who have left the labor force. The labor force
personnes qui sont sorties de la
is the people who
population active c'est les gens qui
say, well, where I work, where I
disent moi bah où je travaille où
would like to work. Uh, and that's the
j'aimerais travailler euh et c'est le le
figure that you  As you mentioned earlier, we noticed
chiffre que que vous citiez tout à
that
l'heure où on s'aperçut que le mois
last month 1 million people
dernier 1 million de personnes sont
left the workforce, and when
sorties de la population active et quand
you look at it, these are people who say, "
on regarde c'est des gens qui disent moi
I'm giving up, I won't find a
je laisse tomber quoi je ne trouverai
job because I'm
pas de travail parce que je suis une
employable, because there's nothing
employable parce que il y a rien à
nearby, because I've been looking for two years, so, well, I'm giving up."
proximité parce que ça fait 2 ans que je
And when you look at that
tomber et quand on regarde sur ce
million, the statistics are
million là les statistiques sont
really very well done in the United States.
vraiment très bien faites aux États-Unis
It's true, we've really moved beyond that in France... well, it's a bit
c'est vrai on a vraiment passé en France
laborious, but
euh bon c'est un peu laborieux mais
when you look, you realize that roughly
quand on regarde on s'aperçoit que c'est
half of them were
à peu près pour moitié des gens qui
over 65. Because there's a
avaient plus de 65 ans parce a une
particularity in the United States: a
particularité aux États-Unis c'est aussi
lot of older people work. You
beaucoup de gens âgés travaillent vous
have 10-15% of those over 70
avez 10 15 % des plus de 70 ans qui
working, half of them older, but
travaillent moitié des vieux mais moitié
also half of them are between 30 and 55
aussi des gens qui sont de en âge 30 55
years old, and within that group, there are as many men
ans et à l'intérieur autant d'hommees
as women. We might have thought that while there are still a lot of
que de femmes on a pu penser queut des
women who work, there are also quite a
femmes qui ét bossé il y a quand même
lot of them.  Nearly 300,000 American
beaucoup aussi près de 300000 américains
men of truly middle age have left
hommes en âge vraiment médian ont quitté
the workforce, so obviously
la population active donc évidemment
this completely undermines the notion of the
cela fosse complètement la notion de
unemployment rate. Here too, it's important to
taux de chaumage puisque là aussi il
know that the unemployment rate is
faut savoir que le taux de chômage c'est
the number of unemployed people divided by the
le nombre de chômeurs à rapportter à la
labor force, not the
population active et non pas la
total population. I'm going to ask a
population totale je je vais poser une
somewhat
question un peu
subversive question: this interpretation is flawed. Do
subversive cette lecture est faussé
you think this is
est-ce que vous pensez que c'est une
misinformation to maintain a veneer
intoxication pour maintenir un vernis
for investors, or to keep
pour les investisseurs ou pour maintenir
a worm in the ground? Yes, perhaps a little, but ultimately, it's simply
un ver ça oui peut-être un peu mais mais
reality. People are giving up, and
réalité les gens laissent tomber et
the indicator you're looking at—
votre indicateur que vous regardez le
unemployment—isn't impacted by
chômage n'est pas impacté par le fait
people leaving the
que les gens quittent la population
workforce. The correct indicator to see what's
active le bon indicateur pour voir ce
happening with employment in the United States
qui se passe sur l'emploi aux États-Unis
is provided in the same way by the
est donné de la même façon par le par le
U.S. Bureau of Statistics.
le bureau des statistiques américaines
You look at the ratio of the
vous regardez le ratio soit de
employed population to the
population en emploi sur la population
total population, and there you have a
totale et là vous avez une chute
dramatic and constant decline since
dramatique et constante depuis depuis
2009 without the slightest recovery. Or you
2009 sans la moindre reprise où vous
look at the participation rate, which in other words,
regardez le taux de participation donc
what percentage
autr dit quel est le pourcentage
of Americans want to work?  Entering the
d'Américains qui veulent rentrer dans la
workforce, and there too, there's a
population active et là aussi il y a une
very significant drop that's
chute très importante qui n'est
absolutely not linked to
absolument pas lié à des problématiques
demographic issues, as is sometimes said.
démographiques comme on parfois on dit
Not at all. You see this in every
ça V pas du tout vous avez ça sur chaque
age group. So it's really the
tranche d'âge donc c'est vraiment la
capacity to create jobs in the
capacité de créer des emplois aux
United States that's weakening
États-Unis qui qui qui s'affaiblit
terribly.
terriblement
Hervé, yes, everything you're saying is
Hervé oui tout ce que vous dites est
correct. And then there's the
exact et puis il y a le renouveau
domestic renewal of the United States, right? The
intérieur des États-Unis hein le
domestic renewal of the United States is
renouveau intérieur des États-Unis c'est
a series of thousands
ba2l c'est-à-dire une série de milliers
of initiatives to redevelop
d'initiatives pour redévelopper les
local activities. There were
activités localement il y avait
8,000 farmers' markets today; there were
8000 marché fermiers aujourd'hui il y en
4,000 ten years ago. In other
avait 4000 il y a 10 ans en d'autres
words, Americans are starting to produce
termes les Américains se remettent à
food, services, and
l'alimentation des services de
education locally again. Why? Because they've
l'éducation localement pourquoi parce
seen numerous studies that have
qu'ils ont vu de nombreuses études qui
been published saying that when,
ont été publiées qui disent que quand
for example, a large retailer opens a
euh starnut vient par exemple ouvrir un
supermarket in a
magasin de grande distribution dans une
town, 13% of the spending remains
localité 13 % des dépenses restent
local, whereas when locals
locales tandis que quand des euh locaux
decide to create something...  52% of
décident de créer quelque chose 52 % de
the money stays locally, so this
l'argent reste localement donc ce
movement is developing
mouvement est en train de se développer
massively, and it's not visible
massivement et il n'est pas visible pour
in the major newspapers or elsewhere.
dans les grands journaux et ailleurs
But there are also interesting indications about this movement,
mais il y a aussi sur ce mouvement bal
and
ba del des indications intéressantes et
as we see in the United States, it's one
comme on voit les États-Unis c'est une
thing and its opposite: they decline
chose et son contraire ils déclinent
in some areas, they
dans certains domaines ils se
recover in
ressaisissent dans
others. There's something else interesting
d'autres il y a un truc intéressant
too, still in the same
aussi c'est toujours dans le même même
source, the
source le le les statistiques du du
American labor statistics. You look at the
américain vous vous regardez le le côté
job creation side, and there's a
création d'emploi et là aussi il y a un
little something there too. They announce a
petit c'est-à-dire qu'on vous annonce un
major publicity boost that resulted in 200,000 new
grandenfort de publicité qui a eu 200000
jobs last time, and
créations d'emplois la dernière fois et
that it's fabulous, proving that
que c'est fabuleux ça prouve que
employment is taking off. Well, first of all, there's
l'emploi red démarre alors première
no job creation, or
chose il y a pas de création d'emploi ou
very little, in what we all call the
très peu dans ce qu'on appelle tous la
reindustrialization of America.
réindustrie isation de l'Amérique il y a
Not a single manufacturing job has been
pas un emploi manufacturier qui a été
created. And if you look at the
créé et que vous regardez que la
majority of these 200,000
majorité sur ces sur ces 200000 emplois
supposedly created jobs, you have  A
créés soi-disant créé vous avez une
large part of it is in leisure activities. I'm talking about what
grande partie c'est dans le loisir c'est
I once called
moi ce que j'ai appelé un jour sur BFM
bartenders and waiters on BFM.
les barman et les serveurs c'est-à-dire
The vast majority of them are paid
que vous avez une grande majorité qui
very little,
sont rémunér voilà et très peu rémunéré
generally earning
c'est-à-dire c'est des c'est en général
less than $20,000 per
des gens qui touchent moins de 20000ll
year. So, with less than
par par par an donc avec moins de 20000
$20,000 a year, you can't do much, you know.
dollars par an vous faites pas
You're practically unemployed, let's
grand-chose hein donc vous êtes presque
say. And then,
chômeur on va dire donc euh et c'est et
looking at the figures by
et et vous regardez après par tranche
age group since 2008, what's quite
d'âge depuis 2008 ce qui est assez
amusing is that it's not the
amusant c'est que c'est pas du tout la
20-55 age group where the
2055 dans lequel vous avez eu le la
return to work began, but rather
reprise de du travail mais c'est des
people over 55 who were
gens qui sont au-dessus 55 ans qui ont
hired. So, over 55,
été engagés donc au-dessus de 55 ans
with a waiter job, you're
avec un boulot de serveur vous allez
not going to get very far, and you shouldn't
quand même pas très loin et il faut pas
count on that for a
compter là-dessus pour que il y ait une
real recovery in the American GDP. So,
réelle reprise du PIB américain donc euh
I want to...  Although there are initiatives here
je veux bien qu'il y ait des initiatives
and there to, uh, create
à droite et à gauche pour euh faire des
local markets and so on, but
des marchés locaux et cetera mais
resisting the crisis, for now we're trying
résiste à la crise en en pour l'instant
to cling to what we
c'est on essaie de se raccrocher à ce
can. Also, Philip, I have a
qu'on peut en plus philiip j'aurais une
question about American debt: who
question sur la dette américaine qui
buys it, who holds it, what
l'achète qui la détient quelle
proportion by country? What
proportion selon les pays qu'est-ce que
can you tell us about it? I don't have a
vous pouvez nous dire
poster with the
dessus j'ai pas d'ffiche avec les
precise figures, but from
chiffres précis mais enfin bon de
memory, let's say the first
mémoire on va dire que le premier
creditor of the United States—ah, well, that's
créancier des États-Unis ah benah ça
the United States. Then the
c'est les États-Unis tiens alors le
second, of course, is China with 2200
deuxè bien sûr c'est la Chine avec 2200
or 2300 billion, Japan with 2000
ou 2300 Milliards le Japon avec 2000
billion, roughly.
milliards grosso
Then we find the
modo ensuite on trouve les monarchies
oil monarchies. So there we must be around Dell,
pétrolière donc là on do être autour
always buying the
deell achètent toujours les monarchies
oil monarchies, yes, by force of circumstance,
pétrolières oui par la force des choses
since they continue to rake in
puisque continue d'engranger du pétrro
petrodollars despite everything. Even if the
dollar malgré tout même si les
United States starts liquidating its
États-Unis commencent à liquidifier le
gas massively, they still have some.
gaz massivement ils en ils en ortent
We have the United Kingdom, which I think
encore on a le Royaume-Uni qui je pense
must hold some  Something like that, 50
doit détenir quelque chose comme ça 50
billion, and then after that we have a large
milliards et puis après ça on a un grand
European country that's also full of
pays européen qui est aussi farci de
bronze, it's Luxembourg, so there you go.
tibronze c'est le Luxembourg voilà donc
But that's explained because
mais ça s'explique parce que le
Luxembourg has a vocation as a
Luxembourg a quand même une vocation de
wealth manager, so many
de gérant de fortune donc beaucoup de
family offices, in addition to their presence in
Family Office outre leur présence à
Singapore, the City of London, Bermuda, and
Singapour à la City dans les Bermudes à
Dubai, often also have a little
Dubaï on souvent aussi un petit quelque
something in Europe to be in the
chose en Europe pour être dans la zone
Eurozone, and so Luxembourg
euro et donc donc le Luxembourg se
finds itself a major holder. But what we need to
retrouve un gros détenteur mais
see is the
bon ce qu'il faut voir c'est la
dynamics of ownership, and right now there's
dynamique de la détention or il y a pour
one holder that's progressing
l'instant un détenteur qui qui progresse
at a dizzying speed, which is
à une vitesse vertigineuse c'est
naturally the United States
naturellement donc les États-Unis
itself, with a Fed that's buying back 77
eux-mêmes avec une Fed qui rachète 77
% of 10-year bonds, and I
% des emprunts de maturité 10 et je
think it's 100% for 30-year maturities. So,
pense que c'est 100 % pour les maturités
Olivier, I'd like to have your point of
Olivier je voudrais avoir votre point de
view on Aubamaker and
vue sur auamaker et sur
Kestone.
kestone
Hervé Aubamaker
HERV aubamaker
illustrates that the United States has a
illustre que les États-Unis ont un
president not inclined to go into the
président peu enclin à aller dans le
finer details of implementation; he has
plus fin détail de la mise en œuvre il a
a strategy, and Napoleon said that the
une stratégie et Napoléon disait que la
Strategy is an art of
stratégie est tout un art de mise en
implementation, so we'll say that the president
œuvre donc on va dire que le président
might not be the greatest strategist
n'est peut-être pas le plus grand strat
because he didn't choose the men or
parce qu'il a pas choisi les hommes ou
women, and in the case of Auamaker,
les femmes et dans le cas de auamaker
it's a woman who is capable, in the
c'est une femme qui est capable dans le
finest legal, fiscal,
plus fin détail juridique fiscal
organizational, and communication details, of
organisation communication de mettre en
implementing an extremely ambitious program.
œuvre un programme extrêmement ambitieux
Therefore, the gap between the amount of
donc l'écart entre le montant des
spending he wanted to incur and
dépenses qu'il voulait faire encourir et
the actual achievement is unprecedented in the United States, to
la réalisation et sans précédent aux
my knowledge. And the
États-Unis à ma connaissance et l'échec
IT failure of the implementation is still
informatique de la mise en place est
quite lamentable in the land of
quand même assez lamentable au pays de
Google and Microsoft. So, of course,
Google et Microsoft voilà bien sûr
how does Kstone, the pipeline to transport
kstone comment kstone le pipeline pour
hydrocarbons, what is it? It's
hydrocarbures qu'est-ce que c'est c'est
very... it's... of course, the
très c'est c'est bien sûr que les les
United States does that. The reality is
États-Unis font ça là la réalité c'est
that the
que les
United States, having now roughly
États-Unis ayant maintenant en gros
covered its oil needs, is positioning itself...
couvert leurs besoins pétroliers se
what is the strategy of the
mettent pour quelle est la stratégie de
United States? It remains a strategy of
des États-Unis ça reste une stratégie de
global power. We can say they have
pouvoir mondial on peut dire que ils
less, they have more, but the
l'ont moins ils l'ont plus mais la
reality is there, and so they are doing what
réalité est là et donc ils font ce qu'on
the British did at the end of the...  In the 19th and
fait les Anglais à la fin du 19e et au
early 20th centuries, since they no
début du 20e c'est que comme ils non
longer had the industrial power they once
plus la puissance industrielle qu'ils
possessed, but still had the raw materials, including
ont eu qu'ils ont encore les matières
agricultural raw materials, they
matières premières agricoles ils se
positioned themselves to remain at the center of
placent dans pour rester au centre de la
globalization. They positioned themselves very well in
mondialité ils se place très bien dans
everything related to distribution and collection. Yes,
tout ce qui est distribution et collecte
we can indeed talk about this
voilà oui on peut parler en effet de de
flash in the pan regarding energy in the
ce feu de paille au niveau de l'énergie
United States. And are
aux États-Unis où actuellement et puis
you referring to the
est-ce que vous faites référence au
New York Times document, those 400
document du New York Times c'estes 400
pages of emails leaked by the New York
pages de mail exfiltré par le New York
Times, where industrial professionals
Times où les les les profes industriels
raise warnings, saying, "
font remonter des alertes en disant
Beware, shale gas may be a
méfiez-vous le gazchist peut être une
bubble. Shale gas has a high rate of
bulle le gaz dechiste a un fort taux de
decay after the 3rd and 4th
décroissance au bout de la 3e et 4e
year." Yes, that's it.
année euh oui c'est ça c'est qu'il faut
New wells need to be drilled every 2 or 3
percer à des nouveaux puits tous les 2 3
years, so the total stockpile
ans donc déjà le le stock total bon il
is far from negligible. We see that
est loin d'être négligeable on voit que
this is restarting production somewhat
ça fait repartir un peu la la production
in the United States, but...  So, you're looking at
aux États-Unis mais enfin voà vous êtes
something with a 4,
sur quelque chose qui a un horizon de 4
5, or 6-year horizon in terms of reserves, and what's
5 6 ans en terme de réserve et ce dont
rarely discussed is that this boom has a
on parle peu c'est que ce ce boom a une
consequence: it's caused
conséquence c'est que ça a fait chuter
the price of gas to plummet. People say it's
le prix le prix du gaz on dit c'est
great that the United States has cheap gas, but there's
génial États-Unis il ont le gaz pas cher
a small problem:
juste un petit problème c'est que
now the oil companies are selling at a
maintenant les pétroliers vendent à
loss, a huge loss. In other words, they're not drilling any
perte et en énorme perte donc autrement
more wells to
dit il ne fort plus de puit pour faire
raise prices. So, by the end of
remonter les cours donc d'ici
2013 or the beginning of 2014, you're going to see
normalement fin 2013 début 2014 vous
a collapse in
allez avoir un effondrement de la de la
production, which will cause
production qui va faire remonter
the price to rise sharply to
fortement le prix à des niveaux de
profitability levels. Therefore, there will be SOPs and
rentabilité donc il y voir des SOP and
Gos that will last throughout the entire
Go qui vont durer qui vont durer sur
period, given the
toute la sur toute la période vu la
specific nature of shale gas. One last
particularité du gaz de schist dernier
point is that they obviously
point c'est qu'ils ont évidemment
started drilling where it's
commencé à percer là où c'est plus
easiest, so as time goes on—
facile donc plus le temps passe donc
2015, 2016, 2017—they'll have to go looking for
2015 2016 2017 falloir aller chercher
areas that are much less
les les zones qui sont beaucoup moins
profitable and much more expensive to produce.
rentables beaucoup plus cher à produire
So, it's interesting.
voilà donc c'est mais c'est intéressant
Finally, there's a kind of small
enfin il y a une espèce de de de petit
cloud of smoke over almost soon, it's
nuag de fumée sur presque bientôt c'est
Saudi Arabia, and then in
l'Arabie Saoudite et puis et puis en
2030 they  They're going to exploit the entire planet, which
2030 ils vont fir la planète entière ce
is completely false given the simple
qui est tout à fait faux vu des simples
geological capabilities of the United States,
capacités géologiques de des États-Unis
sir. The market is bouncing
monsieur de la marche pouz rebondir
back, a bubble, a bubble, as usual, with,
dessus bulle bulle comme d'habitude avec
as Olivier said, a price that
comme le disait Olivier euh un prix qui
was $12 in 2008. We know
était en 2008 de 12 dollars on sait que
they have an
ils ont
$8
8 dollars de coût
extraction cost; today it's worth $3.60,
d'extraction aujourd'hui ça vaut 3,60
so it's quite simple: they lose $
donc c'est tout simple he ils perdent
4.40 per unit. So there you have it, at this
4,40 par par par unité donc voilà à ce
rate...
rythme là
First, you had the
euh d'abord vous avez eu les majors
American majors who went into this
américaines qui sont allés sur ce sur ce
business, and they could compensate with the
business et qui on pouvait compenser par
more
par les les les choses plus
classic things you had. I
classiques que vous aviez je je suis
agree, the Americans exploited a
d'accord les Américains ont exploité un
vein, and as always, they
filon et comme toujours ils l'ont
magnified it because that's their
magnifié pour pour parce que c'est leur
style.
style
But in 10 years, I don't see what will
euh mais dans 10 ans moi je vois pas ce
happen in 3 or 4 years, but in
qui va se passer dans 3 4 ans mais dans
10 years, it's a vein that will be very
10 ans c'est un filon qui va être très
wide,
large
yes, it holds true, even saying... well, I mean,
si si ça tient même disant enfin je veux
today we're in the second
dire aujourd'hui on est à la deuxème
phase, meaning that you have...
phase c'est-à-dire que vous avez des
Major companies that paid
majors qui ont payé des prix pas
exorbitant prices to acquire land and so on, expecting to
possibles pour obtenir des terrains et
make money, realized
cetera comptant gagner de l'argent avec
they were losing as much as they anticipated.
ça qui se sont aperçus qu'ils en perdent
Now they're trying to
autant qu'ils voulaient et maintenant
perpetuate the myth, trying to
qui essaie d'entretenir le myth pour
offload it to followers, to
essayer de refiler ça à des au suiveurs
smaller companies, at not-too-bad prices
à de plus petites entreprises à des prix
to get by. It's
pas trop vilains pour s'en sortir à peu
the classic tactic, I mean, once
prss bon c'est le coup classique je veux
you've made a
dire une fois que vous avez fait un
bad investment, you try to
mauvais investissement vous essayez de
pass it on, so you don't want to say it's
le refiler donc de pas trop dire que
bad. The unique thing about this is that it's not just about
c'est mauvais pour la petite
style. It wasn't the major companies that went
c'est pas que du style c'est pas les
looking for it; it was
majur qui ont qui sont allés chercher
companies
c'est d'abord des compagnies qui se sont
created specifically for this purpose that acquired the
créées pour faire ça qui ont pris les
rights. These companies went public,
droits ces compagnies se sont
saying, "Look,
introduites en Bourse en disant regardez
this is going to be fantastic!" They were then
ça va être fantastique elles ont été
bought out by the major companies
racheté à ce moment-là par les major il
3 or 4 years ago. These major companies are now
y a 3 4 ans majors qui sont en train de
experiencing tens of billions in
passer des dizaines de milliards de
losses on their acquisitions,
moinsvalu sur les achats qu'ils ont fait
but it's all been used to enrich those  who
mais ça a servi à enrichir ceux qui ont
sold the box first in a game of
vendu la boîte en premier dans un jeu de
good luck, indeed you now have
bon tau en effet vous avez maintenant
rights which, moreover, are being depleted
des droits qui en plus qui s'épuisent
because when they don't exploit
parce que quand il quand il n'exploite
the wells, they lose
pas s' ne fort pas les puits ils perdent
the rights. It's very complicated, Philippe. I
les droits c'est très compliqué Philippe
would like you to talk to us about
j'aimerais que vous nous parliez des
derivatives on this extraordinary financial market. What
produits dérivés sur ce marché financier
can you
extraordinaire qu'est-ce que vous pouvez
tell us about derivatives,
nous dire sur les produits dérivés d'une
the volume of perhaps the possible
le volume de peut-être les possibles
threats they represent to our
menace que ça représente sur notre
economy, especially the
économie surtout sur l'économie
American economy? Listen, I'm going to talk about
américaine écoutez je vais
commodity derivatives
des dérivés de matières premières
since we were discussing the subject.
puisqu'on évoquait le sujet alors tout
Everyone still remembers the big
le monde a encore en tête de grandes
speculative bubbles, especially the
bulles spéculatives notamment celle de
2008 oil bubble.
2008 sur le pétrole
Imagine also that
notamment imaginez également que les
gold derivatives represent a
dérivés de l'or ça représente un marché
huge market, or silver and so on.
énorme ou l'argent et cetera des marchés
Derivatives markets on gold and silver.
des marchés dérivés sur l'or et l'argent
Can you specify? Yes, these are
vous pouvez préciser oui ce sont des des
futures, options, certificates,
futurs des options des certificats des
certificates that are possibly
certificats qui sont éventuellement
convertible into physical metal. Don't be
convertibles euh en métal physique faut
fooled, because
pas se faire d'illusion parce que le
most often those who tell you it's
plus souvent ceux qui vous disent que
convertible don't have...  As we
c'est convertible ils n'ont pas les
saw recently in
stocks on l'a vu d'ailleurs récemment à
Hong Kong at the beginning of the summer, an
Hong Kong au début de l'été un
intermediary offered the
intermédiaire proposé effectivement la
possibility of converting stocks. And the day
possibilité de convertir et le jour où
people came, because
les gens sont venus effectivement parce
they wanted pH Global—well, no, no, it's
qu'ils voulent pH global voilà euh non
in Hong Kong, MF Global—it went
non c'est à Hong Kong m MF Global c'est
bankrupt because they
une faillite là parce que ils ont
speculated in a completely
spéculé voilà de façon totalement
unreasonable and
déraisonnable et
disproportionate way. So the Hong
disproportionné donc la société de Hong
Kong company, whose name escapes me,
Kong dont le nom m'échappe euh elle a
completely stopped everything, decided to
carrément tout arrêté a décidé de de
halt its activities, unable to
stopper ses activités ne pouvant pas
deliver the physical stock. And we were, I
livrer le physique et on était là je
tell you, dealing with derivatives, which
vous dis sur des en cours de dérivé qui
are quite marginal compared to currency
sont euh tout à fait marginaux en regard
derivatives and
des dérivés un de devise et deux de
debt derivatives. So today, if we rely on the
dettte alors aujourd'hui si l'on se fit
figures from the valuation,
au chiffre de la bererie
we're between 730,000 and
euh on est entre 730000 et
750,000 billion in
750000 milliards dans cours sur les
derivatives of all kinds, knowing—I need to
dérivées de toute nature sachant il faut
sit down here—that
que je m'assayille là sachant que
605 to 70% of derivatives are
605 à 70 % des dérivés sont des dérivés
debt derivatives in all their forms, including
de dett sous toutes leurs formme alors
government debt.  Uh,
dett d'État euh det
mortgage debt,
hypothécaire
high debt, so high debt in all its forms:
higheld alors higheld sous toute forme
corporate debt, municipal debt,
dett d'entreprise dette de municipalité
which has already been mentioned, and so on. So roughly speaking,
ce qui a déjà été évoqué et cetera donc
if you want the total of
grosso modo si vous voulez le l'encs de
debt derivatives, credit,
des dérivés de dette de crédit crédit
auto loans, whatever you
automobile crédit tout ce que vous
want, it's $500 trillion.
voulez c'est 500000 milliards de dollars
Well, the growth rate is quite
bon le taux de progression est assez
easy to calculate since we had fallen back to $
facile à calculer puisqu'on était
445 trillion in derivatives in March
445000 milliards de dérivés en mars
2009. So, 4 years and 6 months later, we
2009 donc 4 ans et 6 mois plus tard on
're at $730 trillion, $750 trillion. If we
est à 730000 750000 milliards si l'on
continue at exactly the same
euh continue exactement sur le même
pace, it's easy. We aggregate the
rythme c'est facile euh on agrège les
injections from the Bank of
injections de la Banque centrale
England, the Bank of Japan, and the United States, which gives
d'Angleterre du Japon des États-Unis ce
us around
qui nous fait Bonom allant
$150 billion per month.
150 milliards de dollars par mois
So it's easy, right? That's $5
euh donc c'est facile hein ça fait 5
billion per day.
milliards par jour
All of this is invested at 70% or even 80% in currency
tout cela investi à 70 % voire 80 % dans
derivatives, credit, and
des dérivés de devis et de de CR et de
debt. In July 2014, we will
dett au mois de juillet 2014 on aura
probably have  It has reached a current level of 1
probablement atteint un en cours de 1
trillion in derivatives, so what does that
million de milliards de dérivé alors
actually represent for banks and all those
réellement pour les banques et tous ceux
who invest in these products? It's
qui investissent dans ces produit c'est
something in the order of 30
quelque chose de l'ordre de 30000
trillion. That means we're talking about
milliards B ça veut dire quand même
leverage of 25. You have to
qu'on est est sur des leviers de 25 faut
realize what leverage of
réaliser ce que c'est que des leviers de
25 is. That's very, very good to know. And
25 voilà c'est très très bien ce que ça
for example, for
représente et bon par exemple pour des
French banks or many
banques françaises ou beaucoup de
American investment banks, their outstanding
banques d'affaires américaines leurs
loans are leveraged at 40 or even higher,
encours sont sur des leviers de 40 voire
up to 60 in Germany for
davantageem jusqu'à 60 en Allemagne pour
commercial banks. So, these
commerce ban donc voilà c'est ces
figures are truly
histoires sont sont proprement
staggering,
vertigineuses
incomprehensible to an individual. And
incompréhensibles pour un particulier et
I just wanted to
je voulais juste avant de passer la
clarify before handing over the floor why we're using
parole préciser que pourquoi est-on sur
this kind of leverage of 30, 40, 50. Because
ce genre de levier de 30 40 50 parce que
if we don't multiply
si on ne multiplie pas
these virtual debt purchases, we won't be
ces achats virtuels de dett on n'est pas
able to maintain rates at their current level, that is,
capable de maintenir les taux au niveau
2.75 on typical American bonds.  At
2,75 sur des typ Bones américains 170 à
75 on
75 sur
Dubound 2 ET5i, on average in Europe,
dubound 2 et5i pour en moyenne en Europe
these leverage ratios allow for a
ces Levi permettent de fausser par une
plethora of money to
offre plétorique d'argent permett de
distort the price of debt, the
fausser le prix des des dettes le
true price of debt. Therefore, there are both
véritable prix des dettes donc il y a à
absolutely
la fois des leviers absolument
staggering leverage ratios and, on the other hand, another
vertigineux et d'autre part un autre
phenomenon, which is, of course, the dispossession of
phénomène qui est la spoliation bien sûr
debt holders.
des détenteurs de dett est-ce que vous
Could you democratize this information a bit more
pouvez nous démocratiser un peu plus
regarding the volume
cette information par rapport au volume
of derivative products?
de produit dérivés est-ce que vous
Could you then move on to the interest rates,
pourrez ensuite enchaîner sur les taux
the threats they represent, and the
les menaces que ça représente la
position of the different banks? Everyone
position des différentes banques tous
who uses a bank knows that there are
ceux qui utilisent une banque savent
two types of banks: the bank that
qu'il y a deux banques il y a la banque
has liquidity and makes loans, and
qui a des liquidités fait des prêts et
then there is the bank that takes on
puis il y a la banque qui prend des
commitments, which in banking jargon
engagements que dans le jargon bancaire
are called off-balance-sheet commitments. But these are
on appelle du hors bilan mais c'est des
commitments that, until 15 years ago, the
engagements jusqu'à il y a 15 ans le
total assets and liabilities should not
total bilan et h bilan ne devait pas
exceed 8 to 12 times equity.
dépasser entre 8 et 12 fois les fonds
We have reached a point where,
propre nous sommes arrivés à ce que
thanks to off-balance-sheet items, or because of them, the
grâce au hors bilan ou à cause du hors
bank's total equity ratio is now situated...  For the
banque se situe pour les banques les
best-managed banks, it's 20 to 1; for the
mieux géré à 20 à 1 pour les banques les
riskiest banks, it's 80 to 1. There's one
plus risquées à 80 à1 80 à1 il y a un
institution that at the end of 2012 had 76—
établissement qui à la fin 2012 avait 76
listen, it's not a CEORD, no, no,
lequel écoutez là là c'est pas une ceord
we're not going to... So from there,
non non on va pas alors à partir de là
we can say that it should decrease,
on peut se dire que ça doit diminuer
okay? Why did it
d'accord pourquoi est-ce que ça a
increase? And not because of the banks,
augmenté et pas à cause des banques
only because of the governments. They
uniquement à cause des états elles ont
wanted to place the paper they needed quickly and cheaply. Okay, so
voulu placer vite et pas cher le papier
if this
dont elles avaient besoin bon donc si ce
bank-government mechanism changes, what
mécanisme banque état se modifie quel
is the risk for the individual? The
est le risque pour le particulier le
first risk for the individual is
premier risque pour le particulier est
that, uh, uh, the banks
que euh euh les les les banques en
take on less, the governments
prennent moins les les les états
maintain
maintiennent des besoins euh
significant debt needs, and well, at that
d'endettement important et ben à ce
point, rates rise. So if
moment-là les taux montent alors si les
rates rise, as one of us
taux montent comme l'un d'entre nous l'a
rightly said, uh, you, the individual, will be
dit à juste titre euh vous particulier
stimulated to
vous aurez vous serez stimulé à en
buy, but you, the individual, will
acheter mais vous particulier vous allez
half cry, huh? These are people who
à moitié pleurer hein c'est gens qui
laugh, people who cry, because what
rient gens qui pleurent parce que ce que
you invested, either directly or
vous avez investi soit directement soit
in...  Pension funds will indeed
dans des fonds de retraite va se
lose value if interest rates rise;
dévaloriser en effet si les taux montent
the value of what banks hold in
la valeur de ce que les banques ont en
bonds falls. That's
obligation baisse c'est c'est c'est de
basic financial arithmetic. So
l'arithmétique financière de base alors
the risk for all of us is that if
le risque pour nous tous hein c'est
interest rates rise, the value of
que les taux montent la valeur des fonds
pension funds and retirement funds
de pension et des fond de retraite
falls, the assets in which
baisse les actifs dans lequels les fonds
you've invested become less
dans lequels vous avez investi et moins
valuable, and your net worth,
de valeur et que votre actif net
meaning your personal wealth,
c'est-à-dire votre richesse personnelle
decreases. Do you have any
se voit diminuer est-ce que vous avez un
advice on how to protect oneself from this type of
conseil pour se préserver de ce type de
movement? Listen, I can tell you what I've done
mouvement écoutez moi je peux dire ce
for myself: for eight years,
que j'ai fait pour moi ça fait 8 ans que
I haven't held a single stock, not a single investment, and
je n'ai pas un titre pas une oblique et
I've been holding cash.
que je suis en liquide
So, I'm a
donc c'est c'est c'est une je suis
banker, so I'm extremely wary
banquier c'est donc que je me méfie
of your colleagues—not
considérablement de vos collègues pas de
my colleagues—the system, the system, the system, the system. Okay,
mes collègues système c'est du système
Olivier, uh,
du système du système d'accord Olivier
yes, perhaps we could elaborate on a couple of
euh oui peut-être reondir sur deux trois
points, perhaps we could be
deux trois points peut-être pourra être
a little more concrete about
un peu plus concret sur les produits
derivatives. Uh, perhaps we should explain
dérivés euh faut peut-être expliquer que
Derivatives are basically
les produits dérivés sont en gros euh
instruments that, in theory, are
des instruments qui en théorie sont
supposed to act as
censé re des instruments
insurance against the various elements
d'assurance sur les différents éléments
we discussed earlier. They can
qu'on a évoqué tout à l'heure euh peut
also be seen as bets, depending on how they're made.
être vu aussi comme des paris ça dépend
But let's
comment comment c'est fait mais euh
imagine a currency derivative:
imaginons produit dérivé de de de de
we'll place a bet on the
change et bien on va faire un Paris sur
dollar's exchange rate in a year, and I
le cours du dollar dans un an et puis je
'll pay a small premium. If
vais payer une petite prime et puis si
the dollar rises above a certain level, I'll receive
le dollar dépasse tel niveau et bien
money, and if it falls below,
l'argent et puis si est inférieur
I'll have lost, like with insurance.
j'aurais perdu comme pour une assurance
So, it's a system that, fundamentally and
donc c'est un système à la base et
intellectually, is a very, very
intellectuellement qui est un système
sound system that
très très relativement sain et qui
allows you to insure yourself, and therefore, in theory,
permet de s'assurer donc en théorie de
reduce risk. Because, obviously,
diminuer le risque parce qu' évidemment
if I'm a European exporter, this is
si je suis exportateur euh européen mais
a product that interests me because
c'est un produit qui m'intéresse parce
I know the price in a year. That's somewhat equivalent to
que du coup je sais dans un an je
knowing the dollar's price in
part à connaître le prix du dollar dans
a year, or at least to having assumed that
un an en tout cas de s'être assuré de
you know the
faire comme si on connaissait le prix du
dollar's price in a year. So, that's very good,
dollars dans un an donc c'est très bien
but the problem is that  It's been
mais le problème c'est que ça a été
completely diverted from that purpose,
complètement détourné de cette finalité
and those who buy the products
là et que ceux qui achètent les produits
are no longer people who are going to sell
ne sont plus des gens qui vont vendre
products in the United States and
des produits aux États-Unis qui ont
need financial insurance; they're
besoin d'une assurance financière son
people making a bet, like you and
des gens qui font un Paris comme vous et
me. We just say, "Here, I'll give some
moi on dit juste tiens je donne de
money, and if the dollar
l'argent et puis si si le dollar euh
goes up, well, I'll get some money back."
monte et bien je récupère de l'argent
So, I'm making this bet. The
donc je fais ce ce Paris là en clair la
difference is that in the first case,
différence c'est que dans le premier cas
if I'm an exporter and things
si je suis exportateur et que ça se
go badly with the dollar, I'll
passe mal au niveau du dollar je vais
lose money, so I have a risk
perdre de l'argent donc j'ai un risque
of losing something. This
de perdre quelque chose ce produit
derivative product allowed me to insure myself against
dérivé me permettait de m'assurer contre
that loss. When we switched to
cette perte quand on est passé en mode
betting mode, I no longer risk anything, regardless of
Paris je ne risque plus rien quel que
the dollar's level. In theory, whether it's
soit le niveau du dollar en théorie qu'
high or low, it doesn't cost me
soit haut qui soit bas ça ne me coûte
anything. I'm just taking this bet. Basically,
rien je prends juste ce ce Paris là ENF
like I'm betting on a Paris, it's
comme je CIS Paris au cour c'est
exactly the same thing. Olivier Philipp,
exactement la même chose Olivier Philipp
excuse me, Olivier Philipp, could
excusez-moiivier Olivier Philipp est-ce
you follow up on what
que vous pouvez rebondir sur ce que a
Hervé and Olivier said, and
dit HERV et Olivier et est-ce que vous
could you tell me a little bit about shadow
pouvez me parler un petit peu du shadow
banking?  What this represents for
banking et ce que ça représente sur
the US economy and the
l'économie US et sur l'économie
global economy... don't fight to
mondiale vous battez pas pour prendre la
speak, I'll just pick up on what
parole al moi je vais rebondir sur ce
Olivier just said. One point to
que vient de dire Olivier en ant une
clarify is that many of these
précision c'est que beaucoup de ces
bets on bond products are
paris sur des produits obligataire sont
quite typically
assez classiquement des arbitrages taux
fixed-rate/variable-rate arbitrage opportunities with a term of 3, 5, or 10
fixe taux variable à terme alors 3 5 10
years, depending on the maturities
ans en fonction des maturités qui
available on the market.
existent sur le marché
But we're seeing
euh mais euh on voit se reformer à peu
the same kind of bubble reforming as in
près le même genre de bulle euh qu'en
2005, 2006, and 2007 with subprime mortgages. We're simply
2005 2006 2007 sur les subprime on est
recreating them.
en train de les recréer purement et
We're creating
simplement euh on recrée de toutes
derivatives of
pièces des euh dérivés euh de crédits
real estate loans or mortgage receivables from scratch. And it's
immobiliers ou de créances immobilières
not just in the United States; we're
alors pas seulement aux États-Unis on en
finding them almost everywhere now. We're
trouve maintenant à peu près partout on
also recreating auto loan derivatives.
recrée également des dérivés de crédit
Anyway, we haven't
auto enfin bon on a absolument pas
learned the lessons of 2007, 2008,
appris les les leçons de 2007 200008 on
and we've gone right back to the drawing board,
est reparti de plus belle et on est
explaining that
reparti en vous expliquant que
ultimately, regardless of the size of the outstanding amount, even a
finalement peu importe la taille de
million...  billions at the end of
l'ancours 1 million de milliards fin
2014, but in any case, the system is
2014 mais de toute façon le système est
stable since all these bets are
stable puisque tous ces Paris sont des
insured bets. There are those who
paris assurés il y en a don c'est le
take risks, and others who
métier de prendre du risque d'autres qui
offer to insure them, and everyone
se proposent de l'assurer et tout le
agrees that it should
monde est d'accord pour que ça
work. There are those who want
fonctionne il y en a qui veulent du
risk, and there are those who want to hedge
risque il y en a qui veulent se couvrir
against risk, so it can be done
contre le risque donc on peut le faire
almost infinitely. The problem is that, as we
presque de façon infinie le problème
saw in 2008, insurers
c'est qu'on l'a vu en 2008 les assureurs
absolutely do not have the means to
ils n'ont absolument pas les moyens
fulfill their obligations when things go wrong. But
remplir leurs obligations mais on
today, we continue to pretend that
continue aujourd'hui de faire croire que
this time it will go well, and
cette fois-ci ça va bien se passer et il
given the size of the outstanding balance, which is
suffit vu la taille de l'encours qui est
a variation of only 0.3% of the
une variation de seulement 0,3 % de la
total amount down, for example, it is enough to
masse globale à la baisse par exemple
cause gigantic losses,
pour provoquer des pertes gigantesques
and with a 3% decrease in the value of the
et à 3 % de baisse de valeur de l'encour
total outstanding balance, most banks have nothing left on their
Total la plupart des banques n'ont plus
balance sheets; their equity is
rien au bilan leurs fonds propres sont
literally razed to the ground. And what we
littéralement carbonisés et ce qu'on
know in addition to that is that with the
sait en plus de ça c'est qu'avec la
power of computer technology,
puissance de l'outil informatique
when the  Things have started to
lorsque les choses ont commencé à se
deflate, everything is going to happen
déballonner tout tout va aller
extremely
extrêmement
fast. I would say we're in a
vite marche je dirais qu'on est dans une
situation that is much
situation qui est qui est qui est bien
worse than that of 2008 because, on top of everything else, we think we're
pire que celle de 2008 parce que en plus
protected. That is to say, I
on se croit protégé c'est-à-dire que je
think the bankers have
pense que les les banquiers ont
the impression that
l'impression que on leur a mis des
regulations and constraints have been imposed on them, so that
règlements des contraintes qui font que
now we have a good understanding of
maintenant on a une bonne notion du du
risk and that we no longer risk anything.
du risque et qu'on ne risque plus rien
We see this in what is still rather appalling.
on voit ça sur ce qui est quand même un
We see today that
peu effarant on voit aujourd'hui que le
equity capital and ratios
le les les fonds propres et les ratios
are
sont
always determined with the same
déterminés toujours avec le même le même
method, that is to say, when you have a
moyen c'est-à-dire quand vous avez un
sovereign country, it's not a
pays souverain c'est pas c'est pas un
risk, so you don't need to
risque donc vous n'avez pas besoin de
put equity capital against it. When you
mettre de fond propre en face quand vous
have something that is rated by our
avez quelque chose qui est noté par nos
dear rating agencies, which have failed miserably for
cherses agences de notation qui ont
years by giving us subprime,
années en nous collant des sub prime
triple-A rated bonds and so on, well, it's still
notés triple A et compagnie enfin bon
astounding not to
c'est c'est quand même ahurissant de pas
understand that these people are
comprendre que ces gens-là ne servent à
useless by definition and based  A
rien par définition et baser un système
risk system like that is completely
de risque là-dessus c'est complètement
insane, yet we happily continue.
fou or on continue joyeusement
That is to say, if you have a standard rating, or
c'est-à-dire que si vous avez standard
something like a double A or triple A, well, there aren't
note quelque chose double A ou triple A
many triple A's anymore, there's only
euh il y a plus beaucoup de triple A il
Landouillette which is at 5A,
y a plus que Landouillette qui est à 5A
but below that there's not much.
mais en dessous il y a plus grand-chose
But you still have
mais vous en avez quand même aujourd'hui
triple A's and double A's today, and
des des des des triple A des double A et
these are considered
c'est et celles-là sont considérées
unshakeable and not worth
comme indéboulonnable et ne méritant pas
putting any equity capital in their place.
que on mette un peu de fond propre en
So you think you're protected, you
face donc vous vous croyez protéger vous
think there have been regulations, you
pensez qu'il y a eu des règlements vous
think things have been
pensez qu'il y a eu des choses qui ont
put in place since 2008. In fact,
été mises en place depuis 2008 en fait
not at all. So we continue
pas du tout tout donc on continue
exactly as before, with the added bonus of a
exactement comme avant avec en plus une
considerably increased amount of money, which
masse qui a considérablement augmenté et
means that now things
qui fait que maintenant le le les choses
are so tense that the slightest, the tiniest little speck of
sont tellement tendues que le moindre la
dust in there can
moindre petite poussière là-dedans peut
end very, very badly. Philippe, yeah,
se terminer très très mal Philippe ouais
I
je voulais
just wanted to give a little answer about
juste apporter une petite réponse au
shadow banking. So this shadow
sujet du shadow banking donc ce shadow
banking, well, it's
banking bon c'est comme il est constitué
often made up of...  Over-the-counter (OTC) transactions
souvent des transactions de gré àé non
between institutions,
listé entre établissements et par et le
often between
plus souvent d'ailleurs entre
institutions based in the
établissements par exemple basés sur le
United States or Europe, are unlisted. Is there
sol des États-Unis ou sol européen
diplomatic control,
est-ce un contrôle diplomatique un
legislative control over shadow
contrôle des législateurs sur le shadow
banking? Do states,
banking est-ce que les les les les états
ministers, or
est-ce que nos ministres est-ce que
our government have effective
notre pouvoir est-ce que le pouvoir
operational oversight of shadow banking? It's such a
opérationnel sur le Shadow B c'est à
vast subject, I think we'll come back to it,
tellement vaste sujet je pense qu'on on
but I just wanted to focus on
va y revenir mais que je voulais juste
this specific topic of
rester moi sur sur ce sujet précis du
shadow banking. So, the principle
shadow banking donc donc le principe
is indeed concluding
c'est effectivement conclure des
OTC transactions between an
transactions de gré à gré entre un
institution in a country with
établissement dans un pays où il y a une
oversight and offshore countries where it doesn't
surveillance et des pays offshore où il
exist. And why hasn't this shadow
n'en existe pas et pourquoi ce Shadow
banking been
Banky n'a pas du tout été
restricted or regulated at all since 2008? Well,
restreint ni encadré après 2008 bah tout
simply because we've only taken half-
simplement parce que on a pris que des
measures. We created a Volker rule
demimesures on a créé une Volker rule
that isn't applied properly;
qui n'est pas appliquée de façon
it's almost devoid of substance
elle est presque vidée de sa substance
today. But this Volker rule has
aujourd'hui mais cette Volker rol a
led institutions
amené les établissements
to create subsidiaries in such a way that
à créer des filiales de façon à ce que
none  One of them doesn't exceed a
aucune d'entre elles ne dépasse une c
certain critical size that
une certaine taille critique qui
requires it to declare its activities. So
l'oblige à déclarer ce qu'elle fait donc
before, I had my investment banking division,
avant j'avais ma division banque
for example, which generated 50
d'affaires qui faisait par exemple 50
billion in revenue.
milliards de chiffres d'affaires
Now I have 10 investment banking subsidiaries,
maintenant j'ai 10 filial banque
each generating 5 billion,
d'affaires qui font chacune 5 milliards
which are not regulated. So we
et qui ne sont pas contrôlé donc le
circumvent shadow banking. And then we
shadow banking on le contourne et puis
learned yesterday—I'll go back in
on apprenait hier je vais cuer dans le
time—it was on November 17th or 18th
temps donc c'était le 17 ou 18 novembre
that the Fed decided to postpone by one year
que la Fed décidait de reporter d'un an
the implementation of the Volker rule
la mise en application de la Volker rule
as it existed and was designed
telle qu'elle existait t qu' était conçu
for July 2014. It will be pushed back to
pour juillet 2014 ça sera repoussé à
2015, but with intense lobbying from the
2015 mais avec un intense lebying des
banks, we can expect that
banques on peut s'attendre à ce que
this Volker rule, which is in effect by July 2015, will be
cette Volker roule d'ici juillet 2015
completely devoid of substance, with no
soit totalement vid de sa substance
effectiveness or
n'est plus aucune efficacité ni aucune
binding value. Hervé
valeur contraignante HERV
Olivier
Olivier
[Music]
[Musique]
Go ahead, the reality, the reality is
allez-y la réalité la réalité elle est
threefold. The first is that there is an
triple la première c'est qu'il y a
immense amount of capital that does
immensément beaucoup de capitaux et qui
n't generate  That
ne font
increasing and that this flow of
qu'augmenter et que cette plor de
capital is very good, but it's not by
capitaux c'est très bien que ça n'est
placing the money in banks
pas en plaçant l'argent dans les banques
that will have the minimum return, so
qui vont avoir le rendement minimum donc
they do
ils font du chadow banking et ils font
shadow
du shadow
banking outside of banking rules.
banking en dehors des règles bancaires
That is to say, they have teams
c'est-à-dire qu'ils ont des équipes
of men who lend to this
d'hommes qui vont prêter à telle
company, lend to this individual,
entreprise prêter à tel particulier
invest without bank control. That's the
investir sans contrôle des banque ça
first point. The second point is that
c'est le le premier le deuxème c'est que
the banks are no longer able to
les banques ne sont plus en mesure de
control why, but you have to read
contrôler pourquoi mais il faut lire le
Bernardke's book on the
livre de bernardke sur la crise de
1930-38 crisis where he says the main reason for
193038 où il dit la principale raison de
the crisis wasn't
la crise ça n'est pas
1929, it was the fact that from 1932 onwards the
1929 c'est le fait qu'à partir de 32 les
banks laid off thousands of
banques ont mis à pied des milliers de
commercial bankers capable of making
banquiers commerciaux capables de faire
loans, and when we wanted to
des prêts et que quand nous avons voulu
restart these bankers, like the son,
redémarrer ces banquiers comme le Fils
like the father of the CEO of the
comme le père du directeur général de la
bank when I was young, had become a
ch quand j'étais jeune était devenu
taxi driver, so he hadn't been in
chauffeur de taxi donc il ne faisait
banking for 15 years. Well, the
plus de la banque depuis 15 ans bon le
third point is that the reality of the
troisième point c'est que la réalité du
risk is  Hidden at every level,
risque est camouflée à tous les niveaux
right? The banks have
hein les banques ont des pertes en
very significant internal losses that they don't
interne très importantes qu'elles ne
show. The central bank does
montrent pas les banque centrale n'exige
n't demand transparency. The bodies
pas la transparence les organismes
responsible for conducting audits say
chargés de faire les audits en dis
even less, and the general management remains silent
encore moins et les directions générales
in every language. So,
se tèisent dans toutes les langues donc
if we take the remarks that have just been
si nous prenons les remarques qui
made and this
viennent d'être faites et ce contexte
very characteristic context of a lack of
bien caractéristique de pas
information, a fierce desire on the part of the
d'information une volonté farouche des
leaders to continue making
dirigeants de continuer à à gagner des
fortunes, a lack of control, and
fortunes un manque de contrôle et une
general hypocrisy, we see that we
hypocrisie générale nous voyons que nous
are in a risky environment with
sommes dans dans un milieu risqué avec
players
des acteurs
who will do things contrary to
qui feront des choses contraires à
the general interest. Olivier, it's
l'intérêt général Olivier c'est
difficult to bounce back after that, though.
difficile de rebondir après ça quand
The diagnosis is absolutely, absolutely accurate
même le diagnostique tout à fait tout à
and absolutely
fait justeci et tout à fait tout à fait
lucid. So indeed, it's scandalous that we did
lucide donc en effet c'est scandaleux
nothing serious after
c'est qu'on a rien fait de sérieux après
2008, when in September 2008, I think
2008 où en septembre 2008 je pense que
all the bankers on the planet were sweating bullets,
tous les banquiers de la planète sué à à
saying everyone
grosse boutte dire tout le monde a
understood that we were not very
compris que on était quand même pas très
far from a general collapse. We did
loin d'un écroulement généralisé on a
nothing serious. It's...  It's
rien fait de sérieux c'est c'est
really just a
vraiment du
patchwork solution, and even then, some
replatrage et encore dans certaines
measures will arrive in 5  Or 10 years,
mesures arriveront dans 5 ou 10 ans euh
and we haven't done anything, and it's worse than
et que on a rien fait et c'est pire
before. I'm going to give you a
qu'avant je vais vous citer un un petit
small figure about currencies, about
un petit chiffre sur les monnaies les
exchange markets on the
marché d'échang sur la
planet, to make
planète justement tangibiliser un peu
things a bit more tangible. There are 70
les les choses il y a tous les jours 70
billion exports every day on the planet,
milliards d'exportations sur la planète
right? 70 billion is sold, so it's exchanged.
hein il se vend donc il s'échange 70
So we can say that if we
milliards donc on peut dire que si on
wanted to insure ourselves, especially, well, it would cost
voulait s'assurer surtout bah ça
70 billion
coûterait il faudrait 70 milliards
in insurance, and I'm
d'assuranceces et encore je tiens même
not even taking into account the fact that it's
pas compte du fait que ça se fait
often done in the same currency, in euros or
souvent dans la même monnaie en euros ou
dollars. But to give you an idea of ​​the scale,
ou en dollars mais VO alure de grandeur
it would perhaps be at most 70
ce serait peut-être au maximum 70
billion every day on the planet.
milliards tous les jours sur la planète
In 2007, 3 trillion
en 2007 il s'est changé 3000 milliards
dollars changed hands. So obviously, most of it was
de dollars donc évidemment la plupart
just people betting on
c'était juste des gens qui pariaient sur
the yen, right Philippe? We bet on the yen,
le yen hein Philippe ont pari sur le yen
tomorrow it goes up, tomorrow it goes down. Here, I'll
demain ça monte ça baisse tiens je te
give you some money, we'll see what
donne de l'argent on voit ce qui se
happens. It was 3 trillion per day in
passe c'était 3000 milliards par jour en
In 2007, by 2010 it had gone up to 4
2007 en 2010 c'est passé à 4000
trillion per day, and we just got the
milliards par jour on vient d'avoir le
figure for 2013: 5.2 trillion per day.
chiffre en 2013 5200 milliards par jour
So obviously, exports haven't
donc évidemment les exportations ont pas
changed much. So we
beaucoup changer sur sur sur donc on
see that we have a system that is indeed overflowing with
voit que on a un système qui en effet
money, we don't know
regorge de regorge d'argent on SAV plus
what to do with it, and so we make bets,
quoi en faire et donc on fait des paris
we make bets. As long as everything is going
on fait des paris tant que tout se passe
well, as Philippe also said,
bien comme disait Philippe aussi
we can make
effectivement on faire des produit
derivatives, we can make loads of them, it inflates, it
dérivés on peut faire plein ça gonfle ça
inflates, it inflates. Yes, there's always
gonfle ça gonfle oui c'est toujours
someone solid on the other side, there's no
quelqu'un de solide en face il y a pas
problem. All it takes is for one of them to
de problème il suffit qu' en ait un qui
fall for everything to collapse.
qui tombe pour que tout pour que tout s
We didn't do much in 2008.
oule on n pas fait grand chose en 2008
The only reaction from the G20 was to
la seule réaction du G20 ça a été de
make a list of
faire une liste de banques
systemic banks. The G20 made a list,
systémiqu le G20 a fait une liste en
saying, "We have a first list of 29, I think,
disant on avz première liste 29 je crois
or 30. These are the 30 banks on the
ou 30 c'est les 30 banques sur la
planet. We've identified them, the
planète on les a identifié il y a les
names are there. So if a bank falls, there
noms pour le coup si une banque tombe il
A global cataclysm risks
y a un cataclysme planétaire ça risque
dragging all the other banks down
d'entraîner toutes les autres banques
with it, and therefore all the economies
avec elle et donc toutes les économies
that are actually linked to banks.
qui sont effectivement lié aux banques
Faced with that, what do we do? Well, maybe we'll
après face à ça qu'est-ce qu'on fait bon
put in a little more
on va peut-être mettre un peu plus de
capital, we'll see. But the question of
capital on va voir mais le fait de se
how we can accept the existence of a
dire comment on accepter l'existence de
structure, the existence of a
structure l'existence d'une banque
systemic bank, how can we intellectually accept that
systémique comment on peut accepter ça
when it would be enough to
intellectuellement alors qu' suff de
cut the bank into four or four, without
couper la banque en ou 4 à la rigur sans
even resorting to drastic measures, to
même aller chercher des trucs très
say we'll reduce the size,
méchants dire on va diminuer la taillein
the risk of theft
le risque vol
rolls, yes,
roule oui
ENF, so more robust
ENF so plus costud
rolls. Morgan or Goldman think that's
roule Morgan ou Goldman sa pense que
not, it's really not
c'est pas c'est quand même vraiment pas
the happiness of grandeur. In any case,
le bonheur de grandeur en tout cas
the idea is there. In France, we had five
l'idée elle est là en France on avait 5
systemic banks, we're
banques systémiques on est
practically at zero. The United States,
quasiment pas champ les ÉtatsUnis
first of all, has as many as England. They
d'abord on en a autant que l'Angleterre
had five, well, they only have four now,
il en avait CIN bon il a plus que quatre
rest assured. Dexia has just been removed from
rassurez-vous Dexia vient de sortir de
the list for the reasons you
la liste pour les raisons que vous
know. Well, we might indeed reach
connaissez bon on va peut-être arriver
zero. There's only one left in
en effet à zéro il en a qu'une en
Germany, which already...  This is causing a lot
Allemagne qui déjà pose beaucoup
of concern for the Germans. Why do we have
d'inquiétude aux Allemands pourquoi on
four times as many as the Germans?
en a quatre fois plus que les Allemands
Why aren't we being told, "Hey, in this case,
pourquoi là on nous dit pas tiens pour
Germany is perhaps
le coup l'Allemagne là c'est peut-être
a model to follow." Having only one
un modèle à suivre avoir qu'une seule
systemic bank... we see that we're
banque systémique on voit qu'on ne pose
not asking these questions. The main issue is
pas ces questionsl HE c'est surtout
how not to question the
comment ne pas remettre en cause le
system when we know—you don't
système alors qu'on sait il y a pas
need to be a Trotskyist—that it's
besoin d'être trotquiste que c'est
dangerous, it's incredibly dangerous.
dangereux c'est formidablement dangereux
Why aren't we capable of demanding
pourquoi on n'est pas capable d'exiger
the same level of financial security
le même degré de sécurité financière
as we demand nuclear security, even though
qu'on exige de sécurité nucléaire che
the risks are of the
alors que les risques sont quand même du
same order of magnitude? Regarding
même ordre de grandeur sur la perception
risk perception, we saw with
des risques on a pu voir avec les
Edward Snowden's leaks that the
fluites d'Edward Snowden que l'État
American state tries to anticipate
américain essayer d'anticiper les
risks at all costs, even if it means flouting
risques à tout prix quitte à s'asseoir
the constitution and the
sur la constitution et sur les paires
founding principles, and especially its allies.
fondateurs et à s'asseoir surtout sur
I would like to have your
ses alliés je voudrais avoir votre
reaction, RV, on the predatory
réaction RV sur la
behavior in
le comportement prédateur au niveau de
intelligence gathering, whether in
l'acquisition des renseignements que ce
the banking sector or
soit sur le milieu bancaire que ce soit
the economic sector. What do
sur le milieu économique qu'est-ce que
you think?  From a
vous en pensez d'un point de vue
personal and,
personnel et d'un point de vue un peu
more
plus
professionally, perspective, let's
professionnel
start with an observation:
commençons par une constatation qui est
the ability to track all
que la capacité à connaître tous les
financial movements is the result of a
mouvement financier et le résultat d'une
series of technological revolutions,
succession de révolution technologique
and we're not going to dwell on that.
et qu'on ne va pas revenir dessus hein
We can say it's immoral that things are this way.
euh nous pouvons dire c'est immoral
I was an executive accountant
que cela soit ainsi j'ai été chif
at a British bank that
exécutif dans une banque anglaise qui a
created the mechanism for controlling all
créé le mécanisme de contrôle de tous
financial flows entering and
les flux financiers entrant et en
leaving Europe,
sortant de l'Europe
and we were forced by
et nous avons été obligés par les
European central banks to hand over
banques centrales européennes à donner
our daily files to the Americans.
notre fichier quotidien aux Américains
So, what year was this?
donc c'est la r quelle année il y a 15
Fifteen years ago, we would report
ans il y a 15 ans nous nous remettions
every night to
tous les soirs à
Washington, to
Washington
the SEC, or to
le le à Washington à la sec ou à
Washington, or the executive branch—I don't
Washington ou pouvoir exécutif je ne le
know exactly, I can't invent what
sais pas d'cord je peux pas inventer ce
I don't know. What
que je ne sais pas je ne le sais pas ce
I do know is that all these
que je sais c'est que l'ensemble de ces
financial movements affecting Europe and
mouvements financiers touchant l'Europe
the rest of the world were shared
pour le reste du monde était partagé
with the Americans, and the argument given to
avec les Américains et que l'argument
us was that we
qui nous avait été donné c'est qu'il
had to seize the money.  The money
fallait saisir l'argent salle l'argent
from the father and so on,
de la de de de la père et cetera
well, I don't see this situation
bon je ne vois pas cette situation
changing. Do I find it
changeant est-ce que je trouve qu'elle
morally reprehensible? It's an
est moralement condamnable le c'est une
obvious limit
limite évidente
to a
à une
sad hold on our private lives, but
emprise triste sur notre vie privé mais
it is, right? And we come to a
elle est hein et nous en venons à un
second point, which is that it is
deuxième point qui est
because the balance of power
elle est parce que le rapport de force
between the United States and Europe is
entre les États-Unis et l'Europe ne se
not strengthening significantly in
renforce pas énormément au profit de
Europe's favor. Philippe, regarding
l'Europe Philippe au niveau des
predictive behavior on
comportements prédictifs sur les flux
financial flows, what can you
financiers qu'est-ce que vous pouvez
tell us? Is hyper-frequency trading
nous dire la la hyper frequency trading
blocked by
est-il bqué par des algorithmes de la
NSA algorithms? Has the NSA become the cutting edge
NSA est-ce que la NSA est devenue la
of
pointe de diamant des comportement
predictive behavior for the American financial system?
prédictif pour le système financier
I think that today the
américain je pense qu'aujourd'hui les
most successful and
chercheurs les plus performants les plus
innovative researchers... certainly, there are a
innovant al certainement il en avoir un
number of them working for the NSA.
certain nombre qui travaille pour la NSA
I think that Goldman Sachs and JP Morgan
je pense que Goldman sax et JP Morgan
also have a breeding ground of
ont également une pépinière de de
very innovative and highly skilled researchers.
très très innovant très pointu en ce qui
Regarding espionage, we seem to have
concerne l'espionnage on semble avoir
completely forgotten that about ten
complètement oublié il y a une dizaine
years ago, there was an
d'années qui existait
echelon that spied on us from the cutting
échelon qui nous espionnait depuis la
edge.  From the court, no, finally, which
pointe de la cour no enfin qui
spied on all
espionnait toutes les conversations
telephone conversations, emails... well, now we
téléphoniques mail euh maintenant bon on
see that Prism is simply a bit
voit que prisme est simplement un peu
more efficient, right? With the law of May,
plus performant hein avec la loi de mour
I imagine they have a much, much
j'imagine qu'il ont un taux de
higher coverage rate
couverture bien bien supérieur
today.
aujourd'hui
In fact, for a long time now,
euh en fait il y a depuis fort longtemps
and at a certain level, there has been a
et à un certain niveau euh un
collaborative behavior between the
comportement collaboratif entre les
American,
grandes oreilles américaines les grandes
French, and
oreilles françaises les grandes oreilles
Israeli intelligence services. So obviously, there's no
israéliennes alors évidemment il y a pas
obvious collaboration with the
collaboration évidente entre avec les
Russians or the Chinese, who, on the other hand,
Russes ou avec les Chinois qui eux par
might be in a system
contre sont peut-être dans un système
of exchange. Well, everyone is
d'échangement enfin bon tout le monde
spying on absolutely everyone else. We
espionne absolument tout le monde al on
find that immoral or not, that's how it is. What
trouve ça immoral ou pas
can you
marche qu'est-ce que vous pouvez nous
tell us about that? I'll simply respond
dire làdus moi je rebondirai simplement
to what Mr. de Carmois
sur ce que Monsieur de carmois a
said: it's been going on for 15 years,
dit ça fait ça fait 15 ans que ça dure
probably even much longer than 15
probablement même beaucoup plus que 15
years, and we seem to be discovering it
ans et on a l'air de découvrir ça
today, as usual. That is to say,
aujourd'hui comme d'habitude c'estàdire
the French are shouting their heads
que les Français poussent des cris d'or
off, saying, "But it's not possible!"  Are the
frais en disant mais c'est pas possible
Americans spying on us? Yes, they've been spying on us
les Américains nous
since
il nous espionne depuis ça fait depuis
the war. What does that mean
la guerre que ça ça ça vous en
to
particul ça représente pour
you in particular? Well, personally, not having
vous enfin personnellement n'ayant pas
much to hide, I don't really care,
grandchose à cacher je m'en fiche
but it's just not very
complètement mais ça c'est juste pas
pleasant to think that they can
très agréable de penser que on peut
listen to your conversations and that they can... well,
écouter vos conversations et que on peut
now they can also have some
voilà alors maintenant on peut aussi
fun and every time you answer the
s'amuser et à chaque fois qu'on décroche
phone, say "terrorist," and so
en téléphone dire terroriste bon et
on, because it works on
compagnie parce que ça marche sur des
algorithms, and so you'll be
algorithmes et que donc vous serez
listened to and then throw a
écouté et leur balancer après un certain
number of stupid things at them. But I mean, it's
nombre de bêtises mais je veux dire
very unpleasant, period.
c'est c'est c'est très désagréable point
Now, I don't have any
bon maintenant moi j'ai pas j'ai pas de
state secrets, and so personally, if they
secret d'état et et donc personnellement
listen to me, they won't learn
s'ils m'écoutent ils vont pas apprendre
much they don't already know.
grand-chose qu'il ne sachent déjà
So, Olivier Berer, I'd like your
donc Olivier berer je voudrais votre
opinion on the Transatlantic Trade and Investment Partnership (TTIP) on this
avis sur l'accord transatlantique sur ce
point. I'd like to
pointl moi j'aimerais j'aimerais quand
respond, I know it's
même rebondir je c'est quand même
something quite terrifying
quelque chose qui est assez terrifiant
when you look at it. In just a few
quand on quand on regarde en quelques
years, obviously, the principle is the same old
années évidment le principe est vieux
trick of spying here and there,
burette qui qui espionnent deci de là
but this...  What has really changed is
mais ce qui a vraiment changé c'est
the capabilities. They
c'est c'est les capacités c'est qu'ils
now have the capacity
ont maintenant largement les capacité
to record 100% of all
d'enregistrer 100 % de toutes les
telephone communications that have
communications téléphoniques qui sont
passed through the country and to archive them
passées dans le pays et d'archiver ça
easily. Obviously, the NSA is at the
tranquillement évidemment la NSA est en
forefront of this. The
pointe sur ce sur ce sujet là les
reactions, both European and
réactions d'ailleurs européennes et
French, have been very interesting at this
françaises ont été très intér à ce
level. We saw that fairly quickly there were
niveau-l on a bien vu qu'assz rapidement
purely symbolic protests
il y a des protestations pure forme
because, of course, the
parce que évidemment le gouvernement
French government is doing something similar, probably much
français fait un peu la même chose sans
less effectively, much to its
doute en beaucoup moins bien à son grand
regret, because it doesn't yet have the
regret parce qu'il a pas encore les
capabilities. We know very well that this kind of
capacités on sa très bien qu'il a aussi
practice is also being carried out
ce genre de ce genre de pratiques qui
in France.
sont faites qui sont faites en France
So, we can say, indeed, well,
alors on peut dire en effet bon
ultimately, it's true, secrets are
finalement c'est vrai des secrs c'est
unpleasant, I confirm that today,
désagréable je te confirme aujourd'hui
today, that's my concern. It's
c'est aujourd'hui c'est mon souci c'est
not, obviously, immoral, but well, strictly speaking,
pas c'est évidemment immoral mais bon à
we can say moral, where we are
la rigur on peut dire morale o on en est
in our society today, but it's
dans notre société aujourd'hui mais
dangerous, it's dangerous.
c'est dangereux c'est dangereux
I'd like to finish on this point.
j'aimerais finir sur ce pointlà c'est
Dangerous, what happens if, as is somewhat the
dangereux qu'est-ce qui se passe si
case right now, we enter into
sens en ce moment on rentre dans des
less and less democratic regimes? What
régimes de moins en moins démocratiques
would have happened in
euh ça aurait donné quoi ça en
1940? Jean Moulin's Facebook, I think it was
1940 le facebook de Jean Moulin je pense
interesting for quite a few
que c'était intéressant à avoir pour pas
people to have. And it's true that we're also at a
mal de personnes et c'est vrai qu'on est
stage where we see that it's not just a matter of banning it, it's
un stade aussi où on fait quoi on voit
really possible. And if we
c'est vraiment possible et et si on
take a step back, it's quite sad
prend un peu de recul c'est assez triste
because we realize that
puisquon se rend compte que
systematically,
systématiquement euh l'espèce humaine
you give humankind a little something and they'll get their
vous lui donnez un peu de confiture il
hands on it. So obviously, at
mettront la main dedans alors évidemment
first, it will be to fight against
ce sera au début pour lutter contre
terrorism and barbarians,
évidemment le terrorisme et les barbares
but well, we still record
mais enfin bon on enregistre quand même
100% of communications, you never know.
100 % des communications on sait jamais
And you have this on many
euh euh et vous avez ça sur plein de
subjects, you have this obviously, so here in
sujets vous avez ça évidemment alors là
computer science, you have it in
sur l'informatique vous avez ça sur la
biology right now, researchers
biologie en ce moment des chercheurs
are tinkering with the
sont en train de bricoler le virus de la
smallpox virus because sometimes you
variole parce que des fois on sait
never know, you give
jamais euh vous donnez l'énergie
nuclear energy quickly, we do
nucléaire rapidement on fait des bombes
Nuclear bombs, well, for the moment it hasn't
nucléaires euh pour le moment ça s'est
gone too badly, except for
encore pas trop trop mal passé sauf pour
Japan. What will the consequences be in
le Japon ça aura donné quoi au bout de
300 or 400 years? We won't be around to see it.
300 400 ans on sera plus là pour le voir
But we can also be worried
mais enfin on peut aussi être inquiet
about this inability to say, "Let's try
sur cette incapacité à dire essayons
to be a little more cautious and
d'être un peu prudent et d'être un peu
reasonable." I would even say that the
raisonnable moi je dirais même que la
NSA is the tree that hides the
NSA c'est l'arbre qui qui masque la
forest, in a way, since there are 14
forêt quelque part puisque les agences
American intelligence agencies that spy on us.
de renseignement américaines qui nous
They all have their own
14 elles ont toutes leur leur
specific areas of focus. It's bad luck if they do something.
spécificités prè ça porte malheur qu'
So, among these
fasse quelque chose donc et parmi ces
agencies that spy on us,
agences qui nous espionnent alors
some are indeed involved in
certaines sont effectivement là dans
economic intelligence, so they try
l'intelligence économique donc ell essa
to find out who is trying to sign
de savoir qui essaie de passer des
contracts with whom. There are those that
contrat avec qui il y en a qui
purely spy on patents, some that
espionnent purement les brevets il y en
spy on financial transactions, and some that
a qui espionnent les transactions
try to collect
essayent de de collecter du
intelligence on all
renseignement sur toute la finance
opaque finance. But remember this
opaque mais enfin souvenez-vous ce
number: 14 intelligence agencies. The
chiffre 14 agence de renseignement la
NSA is just the largest, but
NSA n'est que la plus grosse mais
each one has its own field
chacune effectivement a son son champ
of investigation, with its own...  Two
d'investigation avec de de de deux
little scandals just to finish, two
petits scandales juste pour finir deux
rants: one against England,
coups de gueule un contre l'Angleterre
which I believe is part of
qui me semble-t-il fait partie de
the European Union and is the gateway to the United
l'Union européenne et qui la porte
States for spying on
d'entrée des États-Unis pour espionner
all the transatlantic cables that
tous les câbles transatlantique qui
pass through its territory. How can we accept that a
passe chez elle comment on accepte qu'un
country in the European Union spies on
pays de l'Union européenne espionne les
other countries, not for
autres pays et non pas pour le
terrorism, but really for
terrorisme mais vraiment pour
economic espionage, mainly because they prefer that we
l'espionnage économique principalement
export
c'est prvisé qu'on qu'on exporte des
stale or corrupted information? Yes, that
informations pas fraîches ou avarié oui
must be it, that must be it. So, bravo to the
ça doit être ça doit être ça donc bravo
European Union! Secondly, Edward
é européenne à deuxième point Edward
Snowden, thanks to whom we
Snowden qui tout de même grâce à lui on
learned a lot, and Povga is in
a appris plein de choses et povga est à
Moscow. They refuse him political asylum so as
Moscou on lui refuse l'asile politique
not to displease the United States, and we were still very close to shooting down the
pour pas déplaire aux États-Unis et on a
president's plane. What was it?
le l'avion du président c'était quoi
Bolivian, I think, I believe,
bolivien je crois il me semble bien euh
because maybe, maybe he was on it. It's still sheer madness,
parce que peut-être peut-être qu'il
and we're doing everything
même une folie furieuse et on fait tout
to discourage whistleblowers.  There are
pour justement décourager les lanceurs
whistleblowers, and Japan has just introduced
d'alertes et le Japon vient de présenter
a law to punish them, so there's
une loi pour punir les lanceurs d'alerte
something that I find
quelque chose qui est euh je trouve
worrying: the
inquiétant c'est c'est la dérive
totalitarian drift in all countries.
totalitaire dans tous les pays
That is to say, today we're in
c'est-à-dire qu'aujourd'hui on est dans
a situation where
dans une situation où on voit quand même
states are backed into a corner, with their backs to the
que les États sont acculés sont dos au
wall. Why? Because they have a
mur pourquoi parce qu'ils ont un montant
debt they don't know how to
de dette dont ils savent pas quoi
cancel, reduce, or get out of.
l'annuler ou le réduire ou s'en sortir
They no longer have growth ahead of them,
ils n'ont plus de croissance devant eux
and today they're backed into a corner.
et aujour aujourd'hui ils son dos au mur
And when it's exactly like when
et quand c'est exactement comme quand
you wound an animal while hunting, it
vous blessez une une bête à la chasse ça
becomes very
devient très
dangerous. And here we are today
dangereux et et et là on est aujourd'hui
with a denial of European democracy,
avec un dénis de démocratie européen
but that's been going on for a few years now. And we're in a
mais ça ça fait quelques années déjà et
state that's drifting away from the system, no longer
et on est dans une dans un état qui a
respected
une une dérive qui n'est plus respecté
because it's no longer
parce qu'il n'est plus
respectable, and it's drifting
respectable et qui est en train de
dangerously. So it's true
dériver dangereusement donc c'est vrai
that now, with the means they
que maintenant avec les moyens qu'ils
have, it risks being  It's a bit
ont euh ça risque d'être un peu
complicated for us, with some
compliqué pour nous avec des choses
pretty unimaginable things. When you see
assez inimaginables enfin quand on voit
that the Guardian, which collected
que le Guardian hein qui a recueilli les
all of Snowden's data, was
toutes les données de de Snowden a été
forced in England to destroy the
obligé en Angleterre de détruire les
hard drives, the police even came to the
disques durs où la police est venue au
Guardian to verify that
Guardian pour vérifier qu'avec un
he was indeed destroying the drives containing
marteau il détruisit bien les disques
Snowden's information with a hammer. What's more, he said he had copied it
Snowden en plus avent dit il aà copi à
abroad, but they must have thought twice.
l'étranger hein mais ils ont dû quand
England, the
même réflch de secondes l'Angleterre qui
country of Vasily Supremacy,
en plus le pays de la vas corpus qui a
asked a newspaper to destroy
demandé à un journal de détruire les
hard drives containing information about
disques dures d'information qui est sur
the United States. I have a question
les États-Unis j'ai j'auris une question
for Hervé. You were
pour HERV euh vous avez été
Vice-President of the
vice-président de la Commission
Trilateral Commission. You just returned from Krakow, if
Trilatérale vous revenez de kracovi si
my memory serves me right. You
mes souvenirs sont bons vous avez
participated in the Trilateral Commission
participé à la Commission Trilatérale
recently. Without giving away any secrets, what
récemment euh sans trahir le secret des
can you
dieux qu'est-ce que vous pouvez nous
tell us about the
dire sur la perception qu'à la
Trilateral Commission's perception of what's happening in the
Trilatérale sur ce qui se passe aux
United States, about the American economy?
États-Unis sur l'économie américaine
What are its recommendations? And please,
quelles sont ces préconisations et
go ahead.  The
allez-y je vous en prie la
recommendation, I would say, from almost all
préconisation je dirais de presque tous
Trilateral Commission countries in Europe and Asia, is
Trilatérale d'Europe et d'Asie c'est
more Europe, more Europe,
plus d'Europe hein plus d'Europe
meaning a stronger, more
c'est-à-dire une Europe plus musclée
structured Europe in the
plus plus structurée dans le domaine
financial field, one that can take
financier qui arrive à prendre des des
measures to ensure
mesures qui assureront la croissance
long-term European growth.
européenne à long terme et et et et
Many European and
que beaucoup de pays européens beaucoup
Asian countries feel that our
de pays asiatiques trouvent que notre
transformation towards unification and
transformation vers l'unification et
action within the
l'action de la
European Community has slowed considerably.
Communauté européenne et de est très
Secondly, they don't
ralenti bon la deuxième c'est qu'il ne
think it will
pense pas que ça va
accelerate. They believe that with a
s'accélérer il considère que avec une
very reluctant England and the ambiguous
Angleterre très réticente et l'ambigué
American stance—which, let's remember, is at the
américaine qui rappelons-le est quand
origin of the
l'origine l'Amérique est à l'origine du
European movement—Jean Menet
mouvement européen Jean Menet à
worked for 25 years in the United States, so it's important to remember that.
travailler 25 ans aux États-Unis donc
They are at
rappeler non mais il faut ils sont à
the origin, but when they see Europe
l'origine mais quand il voit l'Europe se
developing as one of the major drivers of
développer comme l'un des grands moteurs
American power,
des Américains c'est le pouvoir si pe
they
prééminent ils
have behaviors where they are happy for
ont des comportements où ils veulent
Europe to develop, but...  A
bien que l'Europe se fasse mais à un
rhythm that allows them to preserve their
rythme qui leur permet de préserver leur
preeminence, Mr. Béchade, Mr. de la
prééminence monsieur Béchade monsieur de
Marche, and Mr. Beruer. What
la marche et Monsieur beruer qu'est-ce
can you tell us about this supposed
que vous pouvez nous dire sur ce censé
guardian of our problems, this supposed
veiller sur nos problèmes ce censé
advisor to our leaders? What opinion do
conseiller nos dirigeens quelle opinion
you have of the S tanks at the moment?
vous avez des S tank à l'heure actuelle
If you have a S tank you recommend, or
si vous avez un sank nous recommandé ou
if you have a S tank that has made PR campaigns
si vous avez un sank qui a fait des PR
that have
qui sont retrouvés
completely failed, well,
complètement dans le vent ou dans les
about the S tanks, I have
euh sur les S tank j'ai pas de j'ai pas
nothing to say. I would have to say something about
de j'ai j'ai rien à à dire sur les sur
the S tanks. I would already have to say about the
les S tank j'aurais à dire
few advisors of
sur les quelques conseillers de de des
successive governments who
gouvernements successifs qui me
seem to me
paraissent
very deficient, let's say, to avoid
très très déficient on va dire pour pas
saying anything else, deficient in
dire autre chose euh déicient par
relation to their perception or
rapport à leur perception ou par Rapp
in relation to everything. Well, we still have
par rapport à tout enfin on a on a quand
people who hang around
même des des des gens qui traînent dans
the circles of power and who have failed every
les cercles du pouvoir et qui ont échoué
time they have been in a
à chaque fois qu'ils ont été dans une
company. I won't mention his name, but
société je ne citerai pas son nom enfin
he is... and who delivers his
il est et et qui nous délivre ses
thoughts that interest no one except himself.
pensées qui n'intéresse personne sauf
Maybe for years and
peut-être depuis depuis des années et
years, so, well, I mean, and
des années donc enfin je veux dire et et
today, when we see
aujourd'hui quand on voit quand on voit
the actions being taken
les actions qui sont menées
by our government, we can't really say that we're
par notre gouvernement on peut pas dire
following a
quand même que on suiv un
very intelligent path. So, well, you could
chemin très intelligent donc voilà ber
say to me, regarding Europe,
on peut dire à moi sur l'Europe c'est
this debate is interesting. Unfortunately, I
intéressant ce débat malheureusement moi
tend to think that all the
j'ai tendance à penser que toutes les
neoliberal excesses since the
dérives néolibérales depuis les années
1980s have killed the European project because
80 ont tué le projet européen parce que
the European project has now become
le projet européen est devenu maintenant
synonymous with
synonyme de
hyper-financialization, with the Troika, with
d'hyperfancierisation de de troïca de
major tension
tension majeur
between peoples, and that's what led to
entre entre les peuples et euh et ça a
the failure of the current euro.
été fait pour l'échec de l'euro en cours
It will undoubtedly be the final nail in the coffin,
il mettra sans doute le le le le dernier
and it's a shame to have transformed what was
clou et c'est dommage d'avoir transformé
originally a rather interesting idea
une idée à la base plutôt intéressante
of ​​reasonable and
de coopération raisonnable et
constructive cooperation between European countries
constructive entre entre pays européens
into a
euh en un
project, certainly driven initially by the United States,
projet certes poussé à la base par par
but undoubtedly a
par les États-Unis mais sans doute une
very distorted vision. Did they try
vision très faussée onont-il essayer
to apply their own
d'appliquer leur propre modèle modèle
European model, which doesn't really have much to do with
européen qui n'a quand même pas grand
saying, "We're going to create the United
chose à voir de se dire on va faire les
States of Europe." We're all  It's the same with
États-Unis d'Europe on est tous pareil
a German, a Spaniard, a Frenchman—
un Allemand un espagnol un Français
what cultural difference is there? None at all. So
quelle différence culturelle aucune donc
we can unify all of that and make a single
on peut unifier tout ça et faire un seul
country, and since we're at it, we'll create a
pays et puis puisquon est on fait une
single currency with additional strategies.
seule monnaie avec des stratégies en
Some players have
plus où certains acteurs ont vraiment
clearly stated this, saying in the
témoigné clairement en disant dans les
80s that Europe wasn't progressing anymore,
années 80 on voyait que l'Europe
so we're not going to do
n'avançait plus FL alors on va pas faire
what we did for the United States
comment on fait pour les ÉtatsUnis
of Europe. Well, let's create a
d'Europe bah tiens on fait une monnaie
single currency because we know very well that it will cause
unique parce qu'on sait très bien que ça
problems after 10 or 15
va poser des problèmes au bout de 10 15
years, and then people will have no
ans et là les gens n'auront plus le
choice. They'll be forced
choix hop ils seront bien obligés
to go and create our United
d'aller faire d'aller faire no nos
States of Europe, without seeing that
États-Unis d'Europe euh sans voir
it could also fail
qu'ement ça peut aussi foirer
miserably, which is still the
lamentablement ce qui est quand même le
direction we're
la direction à laquelle vers laquelle on
heading in, with an
se on se dirige enfin avec une
inconsistency that I find quite
inconséquence que je trouve assez
criminal because ultimately what's happening
criminel parce que finalement il se
is a resurgence
passe quoi au final c'est une résurgence
of nationalism, obviously. If on
du nationalisme hein évidemment si sur
such a sensitive subject, with the excesses
un sujet aussi sensible avec les dérives
that have occurred in the past regarding
qu'il y a eu dans le passé sur les
nations, you manage to try
nations vous arrivez à essayer
to lump everything together  Well, contrary to the
d'agglomérer le tout euh contraire au
popular will, things aren't
volonté volonté populaire tout à l'heure
progressing much in Europe. The latest
ça avance pas beaucoup l'Europe dernier
poll asked if you want more
sondage est-ce que vous voulez plus
Europe: 19% said yes, and it's fairly evenly split between
d'Europe oui 19 % c'est bien réparti
left and right. It's certainly not
d'ailleurs gauche- droite c'est sûr
a better way to move
c'est pas c'est pas une meilleure façon
the issue forward. So the question is, how are
progresser le sujet donc la question
we going to manage to undo the
comment on va réussir à détricoter les
mistakes that have been made without throwing everything away,
erreurs qui ont été faites sans tout
without throwing the baby out with the Dubai issue?
jeter sans jeter le bébé avec le dubain
How do we ensure that we still
comment on fait pour que justement on
maintain the main point, which is
garde quand même le point principal qui
a minimum of cooperation and understanding
a un minimum de coopération et d'entente
in Europe?
en Europe
We can clearly see that we have
on voit très bien qu'on a des
leaders who are not ready at all.
gouvernants qui sont pas prêts du tout
To backtrack, to return to
de faire machine arrière de revenir à
a powerful Europe, a Europe with
une Europe puissance une Europe qui a
real policies, a Europe that builds, not
des vraies politiques une Europe qui
a Europe
fait de l'erbus et non pas une Europe
that today forbids the creation of Airbus, just as
qui aujourd'hui interdit de faire Airbus
today it tries to create a
par que aujourd'hui essayer de faire une
competing public company, an
entreprise publique concurrente une
American company, and then we'll talk about it again.
entreprise américaine et puis on en
It's obviously completely
reparle c'est évidemment tout à fait
forbidden to create a Eurosoft to
interdit aller faire un Eurosoft pour
compete with Microsoft so that we have an
concurrencer Microsoft pour qu'on ait un
open-source tool to manage our computers, so we know,
soient Open Source histoire de savoir si
for example, if the American president does
par exemple le le président américain a
n't have a button to shut down all the
pas un bouton pour éteindre tous les
Windows machines on the planet—it's called a
Windows de la planète ça s'appelle le
kill switch. Yes, these are
kill switch ouis ça c'est quand même des
topics, questions, and yet we don't talk about them.
sujets des questions et bien on en parle
And even if we did
pas et en plus quand même on en
talk about them, it's forbidden in
parlerait c'est interdit dans dans dans
the European treaties. We've enshrined in the
les traités européens on a mis dans les
European treaties
traités européens gravés dans le marbre
the free movement of capital,
la liberté de circulation des capitaux
which is heresy. It's inevitably
ce qui est une hérésie c'est forcément
something that will ultimately lead to the inability to
quelque chose qui poussera infin à ne
govern a country, since you'll have
plus pouvoir gérer un pays puisque vous
the threat of the
aurez de toute façon la menace des
financial markets anyway. Free
marchés des marchés financiers liberté
movement of capital, which is
de circulation des capitaux qui
invested, yes, very well, but what about the
s'investissent oui très bien mais les
speculative capital we've been talking about for
capitaux spéculatifs dont on parle
a while now?  They can come in the
depuis un moment qui peuvent rentrer le
morning and leave again an hour later,
matin être reparti une heure après en
having destabilized the system. This is completely
ayant déstabilisé est tout à fait
unacceptable. And what do we have written
inacceptable et qu'est-ce qu'on a marqué
in the treaties? Not only is that there, but
dans les traités non seulement il y a ça
unanimity is required to reverse course. It's written
en plus il faut l'unanimité pour venir
in the
en arrière c'est marqué dans le traité
Lisbon Treaty: unanimity is required to
de Lisbonne il faut l'unanimité pour
reverse the free
venir en arrière sur la liberté de
movement of capital. The freedom of
circulation des capitaux la liberté des
people? No, there's no problem there.
gens non ça il y a pas de souci pe se
The freedom of capital is clear, it's in black
faire la liberté des capitaux c'est noir
and white. Look, there's a nice
sur blanc regardez il y a un joli
article on that, Mr. de Carmois.
article là-dessus monsieur de carmois je
I would like to have your opinion
je voudrais avoir votre opinion
on the integrity of elected
sur l'intégrité du pouvoir élu
legislative power in the face of banks. Do
législatif face aux banques est-ce que
you think our states are
vous pensez que nos états sont
sufficiently equipped to
suffisamment équipés pour pouvoir
resist and impose their will for
résister et imposer leur volonté pour
the common good against an
l'intérêt général face à un lobby
extremist banking lobby that is running away on cavalry? What
exent qui court en fuite en cavalerie
can you tell us about
qu'est-ce que vous pouvez nous dire sur
the measures to be taken to strengthen
les mesures à prendre pour renforcer
the state and its integrity in relation to the
l'état son intégrité par rapport aux
decisions made on this
décisions prises sur cette terre qui est
very
très
complicated earth? We need to see if there is
compliquée il faut voir est-ce qu'il y a
a common language, that is to say, a
un langage commun c'est-à-dire un
common objective. And if we take as a
objectif commun et si si on prend comme
hypothesis that  The common goal in the
hypothèse que l'objectif commun aux
United States and Europe, for all
États-Unis en Europe de tous les
governments, right or left,
gouvernements de droite ou de gauche
is economic growth. If
c'est la croissance économique hein si
we take that as a given, then we have to
on prend ça comme hypothèse alors on est
ask ourselves
obligé de se demander
if the banks are playing their role. If the
si les banques jouent leur rôle les
states are playing their role, then for
états jouent leur rôle alors pour que
banks to be able to play their role, they need both
les banques puissent jouer leur rôle il
capital and personnel to
capitaux et des hommes pour pouvoir
invest in SMEs,
investir avec les PME les entreprises
growing businesses, and individual
qui se développent les particuliers
entrepreneurs.
entrepreneurs à l'heure
Currently, the banks aren't doing this.
actuelle les banques ne le font pas
Why aren't they? Because they've
pourquoi ne le font-elles pas parce
absorbed
qu'elles ont absorber des montants
colossal amounts of government debt—not just from
colossaux de dett d'État pas simplement
states in good shape like Germany,
d'État en bonne forme comme l'Allemagne
but from states that are struggling. And
mais desétats qui ont des difficultés et
the states completely control the
les états contrôlent totalement le bilan
banks' balance sheets, and we don't realize this. The
des banques et ça nous n rendons pas
best thing that could happen
compte ce qui pourra arriver de mieux
to the banks is for the states to tell them, "
aux banques c'est que les États leur
Listen, we'll buy you out and
disent écoutez on vous rachète et on
finance all your government
finance ailleurs tous
debt elsewhere, and we'll force you
vos toutes vos dettes d'État et on vous
to go back to banking." In other
impose de refaire de la banque c'est
words, what exactly is
c'est-à-dire qu'est-ce que c'est de la
banking? This is the
banque on vous demande et c'est la
second measure I'm asking you to do.  I would recommend that
deuxième mesure que je recommanderai que
your equity capital, relative to all your on- and off-balance-sheet
vos fonds propres par rapport à tous vos
liabilities,
engagements bilanciel ou horors
not exceed 12 to 1.
bilanciel ne dépassent pas 12 à un ce
This will imply, gentlemen, that you will have to reduce your staff and redeploy
et ça va impliquer que vous réorientiez
your personnel. You will recruit new
vos hommes vous recrutiez de nouvelles
teams to provide credit to
équipes pour faire du crédit à
the economy, something the State doesn't really know how to
l'économie chose que l'État ne sait pas
do. I'll give you just one example:
vraiment faire j'en veux qu'un exemple
the difficulty it has in getting off the ground with the
la difficulté qu'elle a à décoller de la
public
banque publique
investment bank. Mr. Béchad, what
d'investissement monsieur béchad
can you tell us about
qu'est-ce que vous pouvez nous dire sur
the capacity to implement this type of measure given the
les capacités à mettre ce type de mesure
amount of money—I would
en place face au montant de l'argent je
say fictitious or derivative money—do you
dirais fictif ou dérivé est-ce que vous
think that States are capable of
pensez que les États sont capables de
implementing this? Is it
mettre ça en en en place estce que c'est
realistic given the mountain
c'est réaliste face à la montagne que
we have accumulated over these years?
nous avons accumulé pendant ces années
I think everyone around
je pense que tout le monde autour de
this table understands that since
cette table a bien compris que depuis
2008, any attempt at
2008 toute tentative de régulation de
regulation has been systematically
réglementation sont systématiquement
torpedoed, both in the
torpillé aussi bien au Congrès
American Congress and in Brussels. Torpedoed by
américain qu'à Bruxelles torpillé par
whom? Well, by those who actually
qui et bien par ceux qui effectivement
want to continue acting as if they were  To behave
veulent continuer d'agir de se comporter
as before the crisis, wanting to
comme avant la crise qui veulent
continue making a lot of money
continuer de gagner beaucoup d'argent
very quickly on products that have no
très vite sur des produits qui n'ont
real economic utility, and the
aucune utilité économique réelle et le
banking profession is something
métier de banquier c'est quelque chose
that is almost
qui est
soporific; we invest for the very long
soporifique on investit sur du très long
term with
terme avec des perspectives de retour
sometimes quite uncertain returns on investment. It's all in the
sur investissement parfois assez
details, it's very, very
c'est du détail c'est tout ça c'est très
laborious. Whereas if some
très laborieux alors que si un petit
genius has found a new magic bullet,
génie a trouvé une nouvelle martingale
a new algorithm that allows them to
un nouvel algorithme qui permet en
capture a large
quelques heures de capter un gros
spread on some debt derivative in a few hours, well,
écart sur sur un dérivé de dette
obviously,
quelconque et bien est évident que la
priority goes to that kind of operation. We were
priorité va à ce genre d'opération on
talking earlier about S tanks;
parlait tout à l'heure de des S tank
today we'll say that the
aujourd'hui on va dire que l'utopie
realized utopia is that of
réalisée et bien c'est celle de du
liberalism inspired by the
libéralisme inspiré de l'école
Austrian school, except that we've
autrichienne sauf que on
recast it all in a sauce
a refondu tout ça dans une sauce
of ultraliberalism and a total lack of
d'ultralibéralisme et de défaut total de
control. So we've completely
contrôle donc on a complètement
perverted the thinking of the Austrian-
dévoyé la pensée de l'école autrichienne
Montpellier school. All of this was then taken up
montpèlerin tout ça a été ensuite repris
and reconfigured by the Chicago school,
et reconfiguré par l'école de Chicago
carried all the way to Washington by the Bank  The
porté jusqu'à Washington par la Banque
American central bank, therefore, through all the
centrale américaine par donc tous les
networks of influence dependent on the Chicago School, has
réseaux d'influence dépendant de l'école
established a system in which a
instaurer un système dans lequel il y a
few operators are completely at ease within
quelques opérateurs qui baignent comme
very large
des poissons dans l'eau de très grandes
investment banks, notably Goldman
banquees d'affaires et notamment Goldman
Sachs, the elite of the elite in financial thought and
sax l'élite de l'élite de la pensée et
expertise, which provides
de la compétence financière euh qui
practically one out of every two US Secretaries of State, which
pratiquement sur deux aux États-Unis qui
provides central bankers, including
fournit des banquiers centraux donc à la
Marc Carnet in England,
BCE Marc carnet en Angleterre
Vice President of the Reserve Bank
vice-président de la Banque centrale
of Australia, and all the members of this group, have either at some point spent part
d'Australie tous les membres de la fête
of their career
passé une partie de leur carrière euh
in a large investment bank or have worked at
soit dans une grande banque d'affaires
universities where the prevailing school of thought is the one
universités ù l'école de pensée est
we know, the one that
celle que l'on connaît et celle qui
imposes a single way of thinking. So today,
impose la pensée unique donc aujourd'hui
to get out of this, for states to
pour sortir de ça pour que les États
regain control, and as
reprennent la main et comme disait
Mr. Garnois said, for
monsieur garnois effectivement que les
states to take back their debts from the banks
États reprennent leur dett aux banques
and, in fact, regain some
et reprennent en fait quelque part le
control and freedom, because the
contrôle le la liberté parce que les
bankers, the creditors,
banquiers les créanciers tiennent
obviously hold the reins.
évidemment ce tienent tiennent les
borrowers, and I think that in all of
emprunteurs et je pense que dans tout
this there is no chance involved when there is so much
cela il y a pas de hasard quand il y a
money at stake, it's never chance.
autant d'argent en jeu c'est jamais du
So I think that the banks, or at least
donc je pense que les banqu ou en tout
some of them, think that they
cas certaines pensent qu'elles ont
perhaps have a divine mission, that they are
peut-être une mission divine elles
perhaps fulfilling God's work. Those who
accomplissent peut-être l'œuvre de
might think that, well, those who don't actually
Dieu a fous qui peuvent penser ça enfin
think that,
qui qui non quand même penser ça elles
they are fulfilling God's
accomplissent elles accomplissent
work.
l'œuvre de Dieu
I'll cut you off on the subject of God's work... uh,
en G je vous coupe sur l'œuvre de Dieu
I have a question, to move from one thing
euh j'ai une question qui pour passer du
to another, I would like to ask you a
coqu à l'an je je voudrais vous poser
question that may seem
une question qui a l'air peut-être
surreal to you: do
surréaliste à vos yeux c'est est-ce que
you think that the
vous pensez que les
extraordinary behavior that some
comportement hors du commun que certains
traders or some
traders ou que certaines salles des
trading floors have exhibited... can you
marchés ont pu avoir est-ce que vous
tell us if you are in favor of
pouvez nous dire si vous êtes favorable
drug control in trading floors
stupéfiants dans les salles de marché
to prevent
pour éviter que l'on ait des directeurs
fund managers or trading floor managers from
de fond des directeur de de de salle de
taking too many risks?
marché qui prennent trop de risque par
I'll tell you, it's common
rapport je vais vous dire c'est c'est
knowledge that there is a lot of
notoriété publique il a beaucoup de
cocaine circulating in the...
cocaïne qui qui qui tournent dans les
Trading floors, are you in
salles de marché est-ce que vous êtes
favor of testing
favorable à ce que on teste comme un
traders and
pilote d'avion les traders les
bank directors for drugs, like airline pilots? Let's
directeurs de banque sur les stupéfiants
test everyone because
testons tout le monde parce que
sometimes when we hear
quelquefois quand on entend les discours
Mr. Bernard's speeches, we wonder if he's been smoking something.
de Monsieur Bernand que on peut se
So why not? But if he had been
donc pourquoi pas mais s'il avait la
smoking something, he wouldn't be in that
fumé la moquette il aurait pas cette
position.
position
You have many people about whom
vous avez beaucoup de gens sur lesquels
we can ask many questions,
on peut se poser beaucoup de questions
so if we had to test everyone, we would
donc s'il fallait tous les contrôler on
spend all our time doing that.
passerait notre temps à ça
You can also test the
euh vous pouvez aussi contrôler le
President of the Republic and his Minister
président de la République son ministre
of the Economy because sometimes they give
de l'Économie parce que quelquefois ils
speeches that are more than
ont des discours qui sont plus que
curious,
curieux
so we can wonder if they have taken
donc on peut se demander s'ils ont pris
illicit substances or not. Mr.
des substances illicites ou non monsieur
Bernard, yes, of
beruer sur
course, but that's what
sur ser fav oui bien sûr mais c'est ce
I told you. I have a very
que je vous ai dit moi j'ai vraiment une
strong conviction that we should apply
une conviction forte qui est d'appliquer
the same standards to the financial industry
à l'industrie financière les mêmes
as to the nuclear industry, and in
normes que l'industrie nucléaire et en
particular, given what is happening and given the
particulier vu ce qui se passe et vu les
risks taken by
risques qui sont pris par les opérateurs
market operators, it would seem to me to be a very
de marché ça me semblerait une très
good idea.  A very good initiative. I'd like to
bonne une très bonne initiative moi
make a small observation:
j'aimerais faire une petite remarque ça
we've been talking for two hours now about the
fait maintenant 2 heur qu'on parle du
diagnosis of the crisis,
diagnostic de de de la crise des
analyses that aren't all that
analyses qui sont quand même pas très
different, which isn't very surprising
différentes ce qui est pas très étonnant
because, moreover, I tend to
parce qu'en plus moi j'ai tendance à
think that you don't have to be
considérer qu'il faut pas pas peine être
very intelligent to understand what's
très intelligent pour comprendre ce qui
happening; you just need a little
se passe faut juste un petit peu
intellectual honesty and to look at
d'honneté intellectuel et de regarder un
the details, not to be lulled to sleep by
peu dans le détail de pas se laisser
the sirens. I
endormir par les par les sirènes moi
was quite struck by Hervé's remarks
j'étais assez frappé du des propos d'vé
because I think it's the
parce qu'ils sont je pense que c'est la
first time we've seen a banker of
première fois qu'on voit un banquier de
this stature make such statements in French. We're
cette taille qui les tient en français
not used to hearing this in
on n pas l'habitude d'entendre ça en
France. In the Anglo-Saxon world, many
France dans le monde anglosaxon beaucoup
have said it: former CEOs of Citigroup,
l'ont dit les anciens PDG de City group
all those who worked to dismantle the
tous ceux qui ont uvré la démolition du
class, former presidents of Morgan Stan,
classagle les anciens pr Morgan Stan
you can give me a list like that of about
vous fait une liste comme ça une
twenty people of
vingtaine de de personnes de la carure
Hervé's stature who speak about it in France. Why do
d'Hervé qui en parleà en France pourquoi
we never hear a former banker make such
onentend jamais un ancien banquier tenir
harsh statements? It's
des propos assez assez assez dur c'est
already a real  My question is, I'd like to
déjà une vraie question moi j'aimerais
ask RV because, well, we're making a
demander à à à RV parce que bon on pose
diagnosis, which is good, and we might talk about possible
de diagnostic c'est bien on va peut-être
solutions later.
parler tout à l'heure d'idée de solution
My question is, why isn't it being
ma question c'est pourquoi ça ne se met
implemented? That's what I'd like to know:
pas en place moi c'est ça que j'aimerais
your perspective. Why, I
avoir votre vision pourquoi après je
repeat, this perspective where all the
répète cette vision où tous les
bankers in 2008 had major
banquiers en 2008 ont eu des grosses
crises, thinking everything was going to collapse?
gouttes en se disant tout va s'écrouler
We've reached a point where we're not
on arrive à un système on n'est pas
capable of taking
capable de prendre de prendre des
measures, which, moreover, aren't even
mesures qui en plus sont pas
spectacular. It's just a few points; it basically takes us back to
spectaculaires c'est des points ça nous
1980, right? When I was
ramène en gros 1980 hein moi quand je
born and when I was 10, there was only
suis né et quand j'ai eu 10 ans il y
one fixing per day on
avait toujours qu'un fixing par jour à
the Paris Stock Exchange, and it seems to me that
la Bourse de Paris et il me semble que
the country wasn't doing too badly. It
le pays se portait pas trop trop mal il
even had three or three points of growth back then.
même de ou tris points de croissance en
Today, it
plus à l'époque hein aujourd'hui ça
seems unimaginable to say, after all, a
paraît inimaginable de dire après tout
stock has a value for a
une action ça a une valeur pendant une
day, it's the same, it's an
journée c'est la même c'est une norme
accounting standard. Besides, I'm not sure it's not being
comptable d'ailleurs pas sû ce soit pas
misused; we could imagine things.
détourné on pourrait imaginer des trucs
So it's not a revolution,
comme ça c'est pas une révolution
imagine we're going to give a
imaginez qu'on va donner un dividende
triple dividend to shareholders who have held their shares for over 10
triple à des actionnaires DEP plus de 10
years. Why not this kind of simple idea?
ans pourquoi pas ce genre d'idée simple
We can't seem to implement
on n'arrive pas à mettre en place des
common-sense things that have already
choses de bon sens qui en plus ont déjà
been implemented in the past. Where does
été mis en place par le passé d'où vient
the problem come from? What can we do
le problème qu'est-ce qu'on peut faire
to change things? Otherwise, we can
pour que ça change sinon on pourra
talk, it'll collapse a second
parler ça va s'écrouler une deuxième
time, and we'll be able to get together again,
fois et on pourra là encore se réunir en
saying, "We were right, friends." Well,
disant on avait raison les amis bon
unfortunately, like in Cyprus, we have a
malheureusement on a comme à Chipre une
ruin for all savers. Oh well,
ruine de de tous les épargnants oh ben
there is a common-
il y a une réponse de bon
sense answer to move from this. We have, we can
sens pour passer de nous avons on peut
say roughly, the same banking system, the
dire en gros le même système bancaire la
same organization within banks, with slight
même organisation dans les banques avec
variations in IT here and there.
nuance d'informatique à droite et à
In 2013, what about 2000, or 1980?
gauche en 2013 quand 2000 quand 1980
We haven't changed. Why haven't we
hein on n'a pas changé pourquoi n'a-t-on
changed the internal organization of banks
pas changé l'organisation des banques en
in the last 30 years?
interne au cours des 30 dernières années
Take Renault, for example,
alors que vous prenez renult hein pour
or Peugeot, for instance. They...  They are completely
auou peugo ils se sont complète
transformed in the markets, in their
transformé sur les marchés sur les
working methods, in their marketing,
méthodes de travail sur leur marketing
and so on, because we don't recruit
et cetera parce que nous ne recrutons
at the top of the banks, people who
pas au sommet des banques des hommes qui
can lead change. We don't
peuvent conduire le changement nous ne
recruit them; we recruit
les recruons pas nous recrutons des
remarkably intelligent people. We
types remarquablement intelligents nous
recruit people who have attended
recrutons des gens qui ont fait
the Inspectorate of Finances or the Corps
l'Inspection des finances ou le corps
of Mines, but who don't have all the
des mines mais qui n'ont pas toute cette
training that starts from the bottom up. You
formation qui commence en bas en bas il
have to start at the bottom to understand
faut commencer en bas pour comprendre
how a bank employee works,
comment un employé de banque travaille
to understand how the small customer
pour comprendre comment le petit client
reacts, and who, as they move up the hierarchy,
réagit et qui montant dans sa hiérarchie
knows how to lead change.
sait comment conduire le changement
First point, and why don't they
premier point et pourquoi est-ce qu'ils
want to take it on? They don't
ne veulent pas l' prendre hein ils ne
want to take it on for two reasons: the
veulent pas la prendre pour deux raisons
essential part, 30 to 40% of the
l'essentiel 30 à 40 % de du bénéfice des
banks' profits, comes from market activities,
banques provient des activités de marché
and to regain
et que pour arriver à retrouver une
real profitability by reducing
vraie rentabilité en diminuant les
market activities, it will be
activités de marché il va
necessary to thoroughly reorganize the
falloir réorganiser en profondeur la
bank from top to bottom. And for that, you
banque de haut jusqu'en bas et pour ça
have to learn and implement
faut apprendre et mettre en œuvre la
field management. I have a
conduite du champ j'ai j'ai j'ai une
question regarding this
question par rapport à cette
reorganization, Hervé, at the moment.  Don't
réorganisation Hervé à l'heure actuelle
you
est-ce que vous pensez pas
sincerely think we've passed the
sincèrement que nous avons dépassé le
point of no return for an overhaul of
point de non retour pour une refonte de
this banking system? I'll
de cette organisation bancire je je vais
take the case of Fujima: we had
dire prenons cas de fukjima nous avons
a first reactor that went up in flames, yes,
un premier réacteur qui a flambé oui
and the only measures we'll be
et les mesures que nous allons
able to take are
uniquement pouvoir faire c'est des
palliative measures on a globalized banking system. Don't
palliatives sur un système bancaire à
you think this overhaul is
vous pensez pas que cette refonte
so important and so
tellement importante et tellement
profound that we lack the courage, and
profonde que le courage nous manque et
that our political decision-makers lack the courage?
que le courage manque à nos décideurs
But it's never too late,
politiques mais il est jamais trop tard
right? If we
hein si si on on
listened to people from 55 to 60 years old in
écoutait les gens de 55 60 ans
1947 saying, "We'll never have a
1947 dire mais on va jamais avoir une
French industry," I heard that
industrie française moi j'ai entendu ça
all my childhood. "No, no, because there won't be
toute mon enfance mais non mais non car
a French industry,
moi il y aura pas d'industrie française
we don't know how to create a
on ne sait pas faire une industrie
French industry." Well, very well, there have been
française bon très bien il y a eu des
people who led, there have been great
gens menés il y a eu des grands
industrialists, the workers' movement, and so on,
industriels les ples de l'ouvriers et
who have done that. So
compagnie qui ont fait ça donc
today we need people who are assertive, who are
aujourd'hui il faut des hommes qui
competent, and who
affirment qui qui soit compétent et qui
are ready to transform the
soi prêt à à à à transformer les les les
banks and experience.  that I experienced
les banques et l'expérience que j'ai eu
in London where I took over a bank with
à Londres où j'ai pris une banque qui
18 hierarchical levels—
avait 18 niveaux hiérarchiques
18 hierarchical levels, huh? That's
18 niveaux hiérarchiques hein c'est
colossal! It hadn't changed for
colossal qui n'avait pas changé pendant
100 years, huh? Except that its staff had
100 ans hein sauf que son effectif avait
doubled. Well, we did it. We have to
doublé et ben on l'a fait il faut
explain this
l'expliciter on a expliqué ce qui'est
to the English, you know, we explained to them that
aux petits Anglais hein qui qui qui que
we had been the leading bank
on avait été la première banque il y a
100 years ago, we were 28th today, we gave ourselves
100 ans on était la 28e aujourd'hui on
5 years to
se donnait 5 ans
become 10th, and we did it. So all of this is
pourevenir la 10e et on l'a fait donc
a leadership problem, it's
tout ça c'est un problème de leadership
not an intrinsic problem of the
c'est pas un problème intrinsèque à la
bank, Mr. de la Marche. I think we already
banque monsieur de la marche je crois
missed a window
déjà on a on a déjà loupé une fenêtre
of opportunity, which was in 2008. When you
d'opportunité qui était 2008 quand vous
want to negotiate with someone, it's
voulez négocier avec quelqu'un il vaut
better to be in a position of strength. So
mieux être en position de force là
today, what have we done? You
aujourd'hui qu'est-ce qu'on a fait vous
had banks that were sweating bullets,
aviez des banques qui avaient des
as
grosses sué comme disait
Olivier said at that time. We
Olivier à ce moment-là il fallait leur
shouldn't have given them a choice; we
il fallait pas leur donner le choix
should have told them...  Listen, that's how it's going to
fallait leur dire bah écoutez voilà
happen, and there's no other way.
c'est comme ça que ça va se passer et
You sign
puis et puis pas autrement vous signez
at the bottom of the page, we'll take care
en bas de la page nous on va se charger
of filling it out. The governments didn't do it. The
de remplir les gouvernements l'ont pas
governments pulled the
fait les gouvernements ils ont sorti les
banks out of the water, they dried them up, they put them back in, and at that point
banques de l'eau ils les ont séché ils
they summoned them to the Ministry of Finance and elsewhere, saying, "
ils les ont convoqué à Bercy et ailleurs
Excuse me for
en leur disant excusez-moi nous de vous
bothering you, could you...
déranger est-ce que vous pourriez euh
make a gesture and... do what we're
faire un geste et euh euh faire ce qu'on
asking?" What did
vous demande
the banks respond at
qu'est-ce qu'ont répondu les banques à
that point? They simply
ce moment-là ils ont simplement fait
scared the leaders by saying, "Watch out,
peur aux dirigeants en disant attention
if you bother us, we won't lend anymore." Okay. So, since
si tu nous embêtes on prête plus
the whole system is based on
d'accord donc comme tout le système
free money at
repose sur de l'argent gratuit sur des
zero interest rates, which is the biggest
taux à zéro ce qui est la plus immense
mistake you can make because it leads to
bêtise qu'on puisse faire puisque ça ça
a systematic misallocation of assets,
fait une mauvaise allocation d'actifs
and so it
systématique et donc ça se termine
always ends the same way, that is to say,
toujours de la même façon c'està-dire
very
très
badly, and since the whole system is based on
mal et que tout le système repose sur de
debt and the issuance of
la dette et de l'émission dette
perpetual debt, you have a leader
perpétuelle donc vous avez un dirigeant
who finds himself facing a...  The banker who
qui se retrouve à face à un banquier qui
told him, "If you bother me, I won't lend anymore,"
lui dit si tu m'embêes je prête plus il
panicked. He said, "Excuse me for bothering you.
paniqué il dit excusez-moi de vous avoir
You can come back." He could go back
dérangé vous pouvez revenir vous pouvez
to his office. So, as long as
repartir dans vos bureaux donc tant que
this continues, and as long as we don't have
ça durera et tant qu'on naura pas
someone, as Mr. Tapis, a real tough guy, said,
quelqu'un comme disait monsieur tapis
who can
sévèrement burné qui pourra dire au au
tell the banker, "No, it's this way and that's that," well, you'll always have the same problem. Nobody wanted to. Well, we saw that Olivier was very much at the forefront of this, on the banking reform. When Mr. Oua was told that
bancaire quand on a dit à Monsieur
perhaps his balance sheet needed to be reduced, he said, "
peut-être diminuer son bilan il a dire
But for me, market activities
mais moi mais les activités de marché ça
represent 3% of my business, just like that,
représente 3 % de mon activité comme ça
or 2%, looking straight
en regardant ou 2 % en regardant droit
into the eyes of the MP who said, 'Oh really?
dans les yeux le député qui a dit ah bon
I thought it was more, excuse me
je croyais que c'était plus excusez-moi
for bothering you, sir,
de vous avoir dérangé monsieur
for asking you the question.'
de vous avoir posé la question
So, when you have someone who lies through his
donc quand vous avez quelqu'un qui ment
teeth in front of an
comme un arracheur de dents face à un
MP who asks him a question, '
député qui lui pose une question
What do you want to do?' and that
qu'est-ce que vous voulez faire et que
you  You have the MP who, on top of everything else, on the
vous avez le député qui en plus de
other side, backs down, saying, "Oh,
l'autre côté s'écrase en disant ah bah
excuse me, I misunderstood." Well,
excusez-moi j'avais mal compris bon bah
you can be sure things aren't going to move forward
vous pouvez être sûr que les choses
now. We
n'avanceront pas maintenant il faut
really need a political decision, and we
vraiment une décision politique et il
really need someone who wants to implement it.
faut vraiment quelqu'un qui a envie de
And for the moment,
la mettre en œuvre et pour l'instant à
apart from Mr.
part les déclarations de Monsieur
Hollande's statements that his first
Hollande qui disait que son premier
enemy was finance, it's remained just... yes,
ennemi était la finance ça n'est resté
I think they've become
qu' oui je pense qu'ils sont devenus
friends,
amis
and it's just been a statement.
et ça resté simplement une déclaration
You were at the BFM Awards last night.
éid vous éti au BFM Award hier soir
Could you share some
est-ce que vous pouvez nous faire
information
remonter une petite information que
you gave off the record about
vousvez livré en off sur les
Mr. Trich's statements? It was
déclarations de Monsieur trich c'était
very amusing. Of course, many
très amusant alors évidemment beaucoup
people will tell you, "Well, Mr.
de gens vous diront enfin Monsieur
Trich is retired anyway,
tricher toute façon il est à la retraite
and what he said is completely irrelevant,"
et ce qu'il a dit n'a absolument aucun
but it was still quite
intérêt mais c'était quand même assez
amusing. He said three
assez amusant il a dit il a dit trois
things: he said that, in his personal opinion,
choses il a dit que à son son avis
he wanted us to return to a
euh il souhaitait que on revienne à un
fixed exchange rate system, which, coming from the former
fixe qui était de la part d' l'ancien
head of the ECB, was quite
patron de la BCE quand même quelque
something.  The second
chose d'assez intéressant la deuxième
thing he said was quite interesting:
chose qu'il a dit
some people should still ask themselves
c'est que certains devraient se poser
the question. Those who
tout de même la question tous ceux qui
see the recovery and the end of the crisis
voient la reprise et la fin de la crise
could ask themselves questions, because
pouvaient se poser des questions puisque
when all the central banks in the
quand toutes les banques centrales du
world were using unconventional measures
monde utilisaient des des mesures non
at a frantic pace,
conventionnelles et à un rythme effrainé
one could still wonder
on pouvait quand même se poser la
if we were
question de savoir si on était
truly out of the crisis. That was
réellement sorti de la crise ça c'était
for those who saw the crisis as behind
pour ceux qui voyaient la crise derrière
them, I suppose. And the
eux je suppose petit message et et le la
third interesting thing he said was,
troisième chose qu'il a dit intéressante
for all those who are criticizing
euh pour tous ceux qui critiquaient
the ECB today, saying that it isn't playing
aujourd'hui la BCE en disant qu'elle ne
the game of the BoJ, the
ne rentrait pas dans le jeu de la BoJ de
Bank of Japan, and the Fed—that is, running
la Banque du Japon et de la Fed
the printing press
c'est-à-dire à faire tourner la planche
and doing successive rounds of quantitative easing—
à habiller et à faire des qe successifs
he said, and I remind you, that for
il disait je vous rappelle tout même que
some time now it's been an unlimited open
depuis déjà un certain temps c'est open
bar. Those are the words: unlimited open bar
bar illimité ce sont ces termes open bar
at the European Central Bank
illimité à la banque centrale européenne
for banks that can come and
pour les banques qui peuvent venir se
finance themselves in exchange for any kind of
financer en échange de n'importe quelle
nonsense, since we
cochonnerie d'ailleurs puisqu'on abaisse
regularly lower the levels of  quality of
régulièrement les niveaux de qualité des
collateral and that therefore now the
collatéraux et que donc maintenant la
ECB looks
BCE
more like a garbage dump than
est ressemble plus à une poubelle qu'à
a central bank, Mr. Béchade,
une banque centrale monsieur Béchade
yes, uh, the figures speak for themselves,
oui euh les chiffres parlent de même le
the ECB's balance sheet is larger than
bilan de la BCE est supérieur à celui de
the Fed's, well fortunately thanks to J  anet
la Fed bon heureusement grâce à Janet
yen there might be a chance that the
yen il y a peut-être une chance que les
United States will regain the lead, but well,
États-Unis repassent devant mais bon
Mr. Dragou, Dr. Mr. Dragou
mais monsieur dragou Dr monsieur drag
is lying in
est là en
wait, provided he gets the green light
embusc pour pour peu qu'il a un feu vert
from Carl Schou's Constitutional Court
de la Cour constitutionnelle de Carl
for indeed limited limits that could
schou pour effectivement des ltos
effectively be transformed into quantitative measures. Well, we're not
effectivement en quantitativeing bon on
out of the woods yet, obviously.
n'est pas sorti de l'auberge évidemment
Regarding the impossibility of
en ce qui concerne l'impossibilité de
reforming the system, well, I think it's
réformer le système ben je pense que
quite clear: we have what we call
c'est assez clair on a ce qu'on appelle
inbreeding and collusion,
la consanguinité et la collusion
inbreeding between bankers and
consanguinité entre les banquiers et les
very high-ranking advisors, which we find
très hauts conseillers que l'on trouve
not only at Berry, since there,
alors pas seulement à Bery puisque là
indeed, between the Inspectorate of
effectivement entre l'Inspection des
Finances, Polytechnique, and so on, we
finances Polytechnique et cetera on
find pretty much the same people in the United
retrouve à peu près les mêmes aux
States who haunt the corridors of
États-Unis qui hantent les couloirs de
the White House. Every American Secretary of the
la Maison Blanche chaque secrétaire des
Treasury is flanked by
d'État au Trésor américains est flanqué
at least three or four advisors from either
d'au moins trois ou quatre conseillers
Goldman Sachs or
tantôt de Goldman sax tantôt de City
Citigroup. And there's what we call
group voilà et il y a ce qu'on appppelle
the revolving doors system.
le système des revolving Doors
That is to say, you spend a few years
c'est-à-dire que on fait quelques années
in a bank, obviously in
de carrière dans une banque évidemment à
senior management, not in the
la haute direction pas dans les étages
lower ranks, and then you join the
inférieurs et puis on intégre l'équipe
management team. So it doesn't matter if they're
dirigeante alors peu importe qu'elle
Republican or Democrat, or in
soit républicaine ou démocrate ou en
France, right-wing or left-wing;
France de droite ou ou de gauche les
governments come and go, banks
gouvernements passent les banques
remain. So we have this kind of inbreeding, which will
restent donc on a cetteéologie
soon be very common.
bientôt très
And then in the United States,
consanguinité et ensuite aux États-Unis
we have something much more openly accepted,
on a quelque chose qui est beaucoup plus
which is collusion. That is to say,
assumé qui est la collusion c'est-à-dire
since a Supreme Court ruling
que depuis un arrêt de la Cour suprême
that now allows a company to
qui autorise maintenant une entreprise à
finance, quite openly, any
financer de façon tout à fait ouverte un
candidate—a sheriff at the
candidat n'importe quoi un Chérif à
local level, a mayor, a congressman, a
l'échelon local un maire un député un
governor, a senator—it's completely
gouverneur un sénateur c'est tout à fait
transparent. And that, in fact, was
transparent et c'est d'ailleurs é c'est
the excuse:
d'ailleurs été l'excuse c'était de dire
until now we had
jusqu'à présent on avait des des
opaque financing systems, we're going to clean all that up.
systèmes de financement opaque on va
And now, well,
moraliser tout ça et maintenant et ben
we'll know that such and such a candidate in an election is
on saura que tel candidat une élection
wearing a K-Fried Chicken cap,
porte la la casquette k fried chickens
or a Hallyday Burton cap, or a
ou la casquette Hally Burton ou la
cap
casquette
supported by...  A few
bah supportée par quelques banques
influential Wall Street banks, so when you
influantes de Wall Street donc quand on
have both inbreeding and collusion,
a à la fois consanguinité et collusion
you can't reform the system. It's
on ne peut pas réformer le système c'est
not enough to have a utopia where you say you're going to be
pas le tout d'avoir une utopie où on dit
able to change
qu'on va pouvoir changer les Ch les
things or create an institution like the
choses ou créer une institution comme la
Trilateral Commission where you say you'll never see
Trilatérale où on se dit que on ne on ne
a third world war again and
reverra jamais une 3e guerre mondiale et
you'll contain the spread of communism, etc., on a
on contiendra l'expansion du communisme
global scale. You do need
et cetera l'échelon planétaire il faut
a utopia, and you need
effectivement une utopie et il faut des
people to carry it forward. But when all the
gens pour la porter mais quand tous les
people in power come from
gens qui sont au pouvoir sont issus de
the same school of thought—Montpellier,
la même école de pensée montpellerlerin
Chicago—who have all gone through the
Chicago euh qui sont tous passés par les
same paths, who have all followed the same
mêmes ils ont fait tous les mêmes
routes—banking, investment banking, and
parcours euh banque banque d'affaires et
then, let's say, the trappings of power
ensuite on va dire les ors de la
or the privileges of the Republic—
République ou les salés du pouvoir et
well, when you're in that situation, I really don't see how you
bien quand on est là je vois
can reform. So, two last words. We'll
peut réformer donc deux derniers mots on
finish with Olivier Beruet, and
va terminer par Olivier beruet et
then Hervé. You'll speak
ensuite Hervé vous prendrez la parole
to close this debate. Olivier, the
pour clore ce débat Olivier le problème
democratic problem is indeed a
démocratique est en effet un enjeu
major issue in what's happening.
majeur dans ce qui dans ce qui se passe
We can  To illustrate this with the history of
on peut l'illustrer avec l'histoire de
the separation of
la séparation des activités
banking activities, I've seen it quite
bancairesement je j'ai vu ça d'assez
closely. It's amusing, this idea of
près c'est amusant cette idée de
simply saying, "Okay, we'll ask the
simplement dire bon on va demander aux
banks to split in two, to
banques de de se scinder en deux de
do the same thing if they want,
faire si elles veulent la même chose
but each on their own: one that will
mais chacune de leur côté une qui va
lend to the real economy with a true
prêter à l'économie réelle avec un vrai
public service mission, and the other that
mission de service public et l'autre qui
will be a bank, not one that will handle
va être une banque pas qui se chargera
insurance products or
de faire les produits assuranciels ou
derivatives, as we were talking about. In
les produits dérivés dont on parlait en
any case, we'll make sure they don't
tout cas on faire en sorte qu'elle se
contaminate each other." This vision
contamine pas l'une l'autre cette vision
of separation is what existed in
de séparation c'est ce qu'il y a eu en
France between 1945 and, in practice, 1995. It
France entre 45 et en pratique 1995 ça a
was the rule in our economy.
été la règle dans notre économie c'est
Since 1995, in practice, we've changed that,
depuis 95 en pratique on a changé ça
so we put the risks together, and in
donc on a mis les risques ensemble et en
ten years, it went bankrupt. So it's still
10ant ça fait faillite donc c'est quand
a great model. When we say we
même un super modèle euh quand on dit il
have to separate, who says that today? You
faut séparer qui dit ça aujourd'hui vous
have pretty much all the Nobel laureates
avez à peu près tous les prix Nobel
in economics, right? Maurice de Stiglitz
d'économie hein de sttiglitz Maurice
said it, Felps said it.  Nicolas Bavrez, who was
alle le disait felps le dit qui était
Friedman's student, therefore left-wing,
l'élève de Friedman donc de gauche de
says that we must
droite Nicolas bavrez dit qu'il faut
separate, so basically all
séparer donc en gros toute
the world's economic intelligence says
l'intelligence économique mondiale dit
we must do it. I haven't found a
il faut le faire moi j'ai pas trouvé un
Nobel laureate who says how
prix Nobel qui dit qu'est-ce que c'est
clever it is to mix everything up. You
malin de tout mélanger il n pas vous
have plenty of former bank bosses in
avez plein d'anciens patrons de banque
the Anglo-Saxon world who
en dans le monde anglo-saxon qui le
say the same thing about universal banks.
disent de banque universelles dis donc
We've seen it, we've tried it, but it's
on a vu on a essayé mais c'est c'est
too dangerous, we have to abandon it.
trop dangereux faut laisser tomber vous
In France, if you do a survey
avez en France vous faites un sondage
of bank executives, half of them
sur les cadres des banques la moitié des
already say we must separate.
cadres vous disent déjà faut séparer
You have the Financial Times which
vous avez le Financial Times qui vous
tells you, "We don't really like regulation,
dit nous la régulation on n'aime pas
but we can't mess around
trop ça mais là commme faut pas déconner
or it will collapse." We have a system
sinon ça va s'écrouler on a un mode
like this which says, "There isn't a single voice
comme ça qui dit voilà y a pas une voix
except for the bankers currently in office
à part les banquier en poste aujourd'hui
who say we must keep the
qui qui disent qu'il faut laisser le
current model." And in the end, we see that we don't do it,
modèle actuel et au final on voit qu'on
we don't do it in
a on ne le fait pas on ne fait pas en
England, we don't do it in the United States,
Angleterre on ne fait pas aux États-Unis
we don't do it in France, we don't do it in
on fait pas en France on fait pas en
Spain.  It's not done in Italy, though.
Espagne on fait pas en Italie quand même
A real question is why, in any case,
une vraie question pourquoi en tout cas
it increases the power of these networks,
euh ça monte la puissance de ces réseaux
these ways of thinking that
de ces modes de penser qui euh qui voilà
prevent any reform. And
qui empêch toute toute réforme et et
then it's not about making
après il s'agit pas de faire des
speeches about finance being the enemy;
discours sur mon ennemi c'est la finance
it's about saying that finance isn't an enemy, it's
il s'agit de dire c'est pas un ennemi la
people doing
finance c'est des gens qui font chacun
their jobs as best they can.
leur boulot du mieux qu'ils peuvent
Unfortunately, there are no more
malheureusement il y a plus de règles
general rules, no more vision
générales il y a plus de vision
of the common good, and so when everyone
d'intérêt général et donc quand chacun
follows their own small, self-interest, it doesn't create
suit son petit intérêt particulier ça
collective well-being at all;
fait pas du tout un bien-être collectif
it creates bankruptcy, long-
ça fait une faillite une faillite à long
term bankruptcy. The
terme he le mot de la fin
final word is that we're talking about
mot de la fin c'est que nous parlons
money, and money is like the
d'argent et que l'argent c'est comme la
language of the HES; it's the source of all goods
langue des HES c'est la source de tous
and all words. Well, if we
les biens et de tous les mots bon si on
take France, we can say that
prend la France on peut dire que dans
overall we've managed our
l'ensemble nous avons bien géré nos
banking systems well; we've managed them better
systèmes bancaires nous les avons mieux
than the rest of Europe,
géré que le reste de l'Europe
certainly better than the
certainement mieux géré que les
United States, and infinitely better than
États-Unis et infiniment mieux géré que
Japan. So, we've generally had
le Japon donc acte que nous avons dans
a Bank of  France and its
l'ensemble eu une Banque de France et
bankers, who have been prudent, still
des banquiers qui ont été prudents reste
need to do what to continue
que doivent-ils faire pour continuer à
contributing to growth in
contribuer à la croissance et de la
France and Europe:
France et de l'Europe diminuer la
reduce finance and
finance diminuer la finance et
redirect internal resources, both
réorienter les ressources internes en
human and capital, towards
homme et en capitaux vers
industrialization,
l'industrialisation le commerce
international trade, and investment. I
international l'investissement et je
think that in France, there has been a growing
pense en France que
awareness
il y a un une prise de conscience depuis
among bankers over the past five years that this is
5 ans chez les banquiers que c'est ça
their primary mission, which makes me
leur mission principale ce qui fait que
quite optimistic about the future of
je suis assez optimiste sur l'avenir de
French and
l'activité bancaire française et de
European banking. Very well,
l'activité bancaire européenne très bien
society... I'm sorry, I didn't mean to
sociét je suis désolé je voulais pas
jump in, but I do
rebondir dessus mais en tout cas moi
n't share the same view at all
j'ai pas du tout la même vision sur le
that our bankers have
fait que nos banquiers se sont bien
behaved well. Just look at Société
comportés il y a qu'à regarder Société
Générale in Faerkerverviel; they had a
Générale à faerkererviel ils ont fait
SATER debacle once in 2008 (AIG counterparty), and
SATER une fois en 2008 contrepartie AIG
they almost collapsed a second time
ils ont failli sauter une deuxième fois
in 2008. Dexia went bankrupt, and Crédit
en 2008 Dexia a fait faillite le Crédit
Agricole lost a significant amount in the process.
Agricole a perdu un bras en allance
Ask yourself why Greece has 100 trillion euros in
demande pourquoi en Grèce on a 100000
derivatives, while France has...
milliards de produits dérivés en France
Four systemic banks, so that's it. Anyway,
dans nos quatre banques systémiques
I have a disagreement
voilà donc tout cas j'ai un désaccord
here on this point regarding
ici sur ce sur ce point là au niveau de
the management of the relative banking system, you know.
la gestion du système bancaire relatif
We're not good or bad, we're
hein on n'est pas bon ou mauvais on est
better than others. Please specify if
meilleur que les autres préciser d' si
you want. Okay, uh,
vous voulez d'accord euh
I wish you an excellent day
je vous souhaite une excellente journée
and I hope to see you soon, and thank you.
et j'espère à bientôt et merci
[Music] There aren't
[Musique]
many guys like Kusa, this
pas il y en a pas beaucoup cette espèce
incredible Adonis-like figure who, looking everyone
d'aplon incroyable avec lequel les les
in the eye,
yeux dans les yeux de tout le monde il a
said, "I'm not lying, you can believe me,"
dit je ne mens pas vous pouvez me croire
and so on. There was something about it: how
et cetera il y avait un truc comment
can we imagine that a politician would be
peut-on imaginer que un politicien va
able to say, "No, no,
être en mesure de se dire non non
wait, the general interest is the
attendez l'intérêt général c'est la
defense of fundamental freedoms.
défense des libertés fondamental liberté
Fundamental freedom is the defense of
fondament c'est la défense de la vie
privacy," and there's a
privée et là il y a un
conflict there. It's impossible in France. The
conflit c'est impossible en France le
problem is that the
problème c'est que le
movement is demonized; we simply forget that these are
motur diabolisé on oublie simplement que
people who prioritize
ce sont des gens qui privilégient les
results over methods and who are
résultats sur les méthodes et qui sont
capable of gaining an
capables de gagner une connaissance
intimate knowledge of a system.
intime d'un système